<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true choice of a friend. Shewing the comfort of a faithfull friend. : A friend is neerer then a brother..</title>
            <title>Reasons metamorphosis and restauration</title>
            <author>Goldwell, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 150 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S92716</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">60449188</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 60449188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181270</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07702)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181270)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2184:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true choice of a friend. Shewing the comfort of a faithfull friend. : A friend is neerer then a brother..</title>
                  <title>Reasons metamorphosis and restauration</title>
                  <author>Goldwell, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 174, [12], 68, 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Beniamin Fisher, and are to be sold at the signe of theTalbot, in Pater-noster-Row.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>[Part 2] has special t.-p. which reads: Choyce, and applications, which may serue partly for the vse of the precedent treatise ... by Charles Goldwel ...  London, Prined [sic] by Bernard Alsop for Iohn Pyper, 1621.</note>
                  <note>Appears to be a copy of his Reasons metamorphosis and restauration (printed for J. Pyper in 1621) with a new title page substituted for the original one.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: 1 or more leaves between A 5 and B 1 wanting; tightly bound, with loss of print..</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
                  <note>[pt.1] Reasons metamorphosis and restauration. -- [pt.2] Choyce, and applications. -- [pt.3] My friend.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Friendship.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:1"/>
                  <p>THE TRVE CHOICE of a FRIEND. Shewing the Comfort of a faithfull Friend.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>A Friend is neerer then a Brother.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Beniamin Fiſher,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the <hi>Talbot,</hi> in <hi>Pater-noſter-Row.</hi> 1625.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Lionell Cranfield</hi> Knight, Maiſter of his Maieſties Court of Wardes, and Liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and one of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties <hi>moſt Honourable Priuie Councell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHat I haue read of <hi>Siſimus;</hi> expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience reſolues mee of your Honour: that you are temperate, vertuous, liberall: whereof my ſight, hearing, feeling, haue made me, a ſenſible,
<pb facs="tcp:181270:3"/>and iuſt witneſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though I were often diſcouraged, whileſt my vnpractiſed hand was tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling in this Tract, and thought (as <hi>Dauid,</hi> when he put off <hi>Sauls</hi> armour, becauſe he could not goe with it, beeing not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed) to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, with the loſſe of ſome paines: eſpecially ſeeing, both opportunity, place, and requiſite furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, were wanting to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour my attempt: yet theſe reaſons, not ceaſing to allure me, I followed them, faintly (as I could) ſo far, as any time would
<pb facs="tcp:181270:3"/>giue mee leaue; For as there can be none, more challenging then your Honour: ſo great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, freely deignd vnto me: ſo would my negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence (at leſt to ſtriue, in ſome meaſure) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite them, I conſidered, ſprinkle me, with the fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt blemiſh of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. And finding your Honour ſo fit a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, in regard of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious temper of your mind, to Patronize a Worke of this nature, which handleth that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient argument, giuen at the firſt conqueſt, of our
<pb facs="tcp:181270:4"/>firſt Parents in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den (Pleaſure; and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition) (both ſo inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, to their nobleſt wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, and mightieſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring after the fleſh, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in this reſpect noteth, their condition to be moſt dangerous: and conſequently, that they haue moſt neede of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to be put in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance) whereof I haue apertly, and briefly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played the vanity: as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the maine, and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed aduerſaries of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable care, of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous duties; I humbly craue your Honourable
<pb facs="tcp:181270:4"/>acceptance of it: that it paſſing vnder the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of ſuch vertue, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may bee animated, (like <hi>Adonijah</hi> flying for the ſafegaurd of his life, to the hornes of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar) to haſten from theſe extreames, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and ſafe Pillars of Temperance, and a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reioycing, which I haue like wiſe pitched vp vnto their view, and theſe will be able, as to defend them from infamy in this life: ſo to preſent them blameleſſe, in the day of our common apperance. I muſt acknowledge my
<pb facs="tcp:181270:5"/>ſelfe to haue written this Treatiſe, in a boiſterous Tempeſt, that by looking downeward, I might not ſee the threatning clouds ouer my head, nor great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare their fall: therein imitating <hi>Vliſſes;</hi> that ſtopped his eares with wax; and would be tied to the maine maſt of his ſhip, that he might not heare the <hi>Sirens</hi> to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: ſo haue I put of with ſilence, occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by this imployment, the buſie whiſperings, and ſometimes the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like clamors, of a diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered multitude: that I
<pb facs="tcp:181270:5"/>might reteine patience, in their higheſt diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which was kindled with no other fire, but of mine earneſt, and double induſtry, in ſeruing two allied Chappels in one day. For which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, I knowing theſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of mine, vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ſo graue, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued a iudgement: ſubmisſly deſire, that the ſinceritie of my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may rectifie, or at leaſt excuſe my faultes, as your Honour ſhall meete with them. The Lord ſpeake peace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſoule: and grant
<pb facs="tcp:181270:6"/>your Honour many proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous dayes on earth, that God may bee glorified in you, you in his Chriſt.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Honours moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deuoted in all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſeruice.</hi> Charles Goldwell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:181270:6"/>
                  <head>REASONS <hi>Metamorphoſis, and Reſtauration.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MAN (if relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſht to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to the verieſt Brute for immanity (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) whom <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> affirmeth to be the worſt of all Euils;
<note place="margin">Nulla ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manior fera ſi ſibi relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queretur.</note> for as much as euery irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall creature hath but one euill <hi>(&amp; propriè)</hi> of propertie belonging to it, but Man abounds in al:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:181270:7"/>So that though he waſh him with <hi>Niter,</hi> and take him much Sope, yet <hi>his iniquity is marked before God, Ierem.</hi> 2.22.</p>
                  <p>Now the firſt thing that tranſports the minde, from ſetling on the moſt ſetled, and ſweeteſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe; is voluptuouſnes; His <hi>Reaſon</hi> in the Infancy approueth leaſt the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of manners, diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <hi>Pleaſures</hi> beſt: and this is warranted from the pretence of weakneſſe, which refuſeth laudable, and vertuous actions, as too difficult, ſuch as moſt barren of content; and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:181270:7"/>ſucketh on the breaſt of delights, as onely ſutable to the tenderneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. In the growth and maturitie, when it is able to diſtinguiſh according to the worth, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of things, &amp; ſhould therefore make diſcretion of it ſelfe, from that meere nature which is in Brutes, not onely in the appetite, but alſo in the choiſe, and proſecuting of good: then the obiects of <hi>Pleaſure</hi> grow more ſpecious and delectable in our eyes, and we more diligent to execute her vnlawful mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: for that we are then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:181270:8"/>cunning to diſcharge our parts with her.</p>
                  <p>This proceeds not from the debilitie of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but partly from the force of allurements, which are in <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> and partly from Natures refractarie headineſſe, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing gotten ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> will bee ruled no longer by it; for ſo it appeares, Nature is the Beaſt, Reaſon the Bridle, and Man holds the Reines; Man ſits faſt vpon the Beaſt, but heere loſeth the reputation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, in that he cannot
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:181270:8"/>curbe and guide it as he ſhould; but ſuffers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be run away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: ſo preuenting the due efficacy, and genuine ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Reaſon, through vnskilfulneſſe to vſe it.</p>
                  <p>Behold then <hi>Pleaſure,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Her polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</note> amiably adorned with whatſoeuer may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the ſenſes, ſtands ſweetly inuiting: <hi>Her lips drop as an Hony combe, and her mouth is more ſoft then oyle: Prou.</hi> 15.12. Licentious Nature runs laſciuiouſly vnto her, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Man is carried vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently with it, and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:181270:9"/>Reaſon, as a dumbe Picture, muſt neither ſee nor ſpeake, that beſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the ſoule, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily put to ſilence.</p>
                  <p>This hath aduanced the head of Pleaſure;
<note place="margin">Her prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> There is not a vanitie in her ſhop, but cries out to our ſhame, <hi>In me turbaruunt luxurioſa, proci:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <l>A wanton troupe,</l>
                  <l>incenſt with luſt,</l>
                  <l>(with hearts reſolu'd)</l>
                  <l>vpon me thruſt.</l>
                  <p>So ſhe hauing fortified her ſelfe, with friends of all ſorts, the <hi>Preſidents</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:181270:9"/>haue chiefely giuen her preferment, and now ſhe ſits as a Lady, and ſaith; I am, and none elſe, I ſhall not ſit as a Widow, nor ſee the loſſe of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
                  <p>It was woe with <hi>Rahel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Her proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> with many naturall and godly Mothers, in the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tempeſt of their teares which fell for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, becauſe they were not; But Pleaſure is an Harlot, and ſpeeds bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not ſubiect to this loſſe, not capable of this ſorrow; ſhe is euer in youth and luſt, euer preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and euer bringing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:181270:10"/>forth: if ſhe bury one, ſhe hath one borne: if ſhe loſe an hundred for one, ſhe bewailes them not; being ſure of a motherly reſpect, ſo long as but one liueth. For her dition and command is as ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly extended as our Earth, <hi>Super Garamantas, &amp; Indos proſert imperium</hi> It was ſaid to the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Woman, whom <hi>Salomon</hi> maried (being a Type of a Chriſts Church) ſhee ſhould haue Children,
<note place="margin">As far forth as it conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fted of the Gentiles.</note> whom ſhe ſhould make Princes through all the earth, <hi>Pſal</hi> 45.16. This inuerted is verified of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:181270:10"/>Pleaſure, as the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Church-robber: there are Princes in all Lands whom ſhe makes her Children; this good lucke hath ſhee with her honour, to ſee an infinite augmentation of it, and bring al the world to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry for her ſake, whilſt it paſſeth that ſacred teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of her, which the <hi>Epheſians</hi> prophanely of their <hi>Diana: Great is vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As <hi>Ionathan</hi> loued <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</note> ſo are our hearts knit to pleaſure, and we loue it as our owne ſoules: when they parted they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:181270:11"/>wept, till <hi>Dauid</hi> exceeded; if any ſiniſter caſualty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſter vs from our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, we wring the hands, with ſighes and teares, pining in diſcontent, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to diſpaire; ſhall wee receiue good at the hands of God, and not be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of the euill? No, wee muſt haue health, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſeaſe; wealth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out want; libertie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſtraint; friends, without failing, or elſe our paſſion breakes out ſo farre beyond the bounds of patience, that no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation can appeaſe it, nor comfort arreſt it,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:181270:11"/>til it be wearied with that carefull and bootleſſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legie of a too fond Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Oh our Pleaſure, would God we had dyed when wee parted from thee.</p>
                  <p>Although She gaines this vniuerſall loue, by the inceſtuous proſtituting her ſelfe to her whole progeny, ſo many as haue but the leaſt <hi>vndè,</hi> to pay her with all: (leauing the reſt, as the careleſſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrich doth her Egges, in the ſands of hourely dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and aduerſitie) yet the more Noble and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table the perſonages are,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:181270:12"/>the more obſequiouſly doth ſhe incline to their condition, preſenting her ſelfe fairer then her ſelfe, with an artificiall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plection; and framing her dittie in a ſtately and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall ſtile vnto them: and for as much as diuers are diuerſly affected, ſome loue her at home; others would enioy her abroad; ſhe hath her ſeuerall ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the coaſts of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Countries, where (like the tempting bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes of
<note n="a" place="margin">A tree, whoſe bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes are poyſon.</note> 
                     <hi>Alpina,</hi> or the faire ſeeming fruit of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>) ſhe pronounceth her <hi>huc ades;</hi> come hither
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:181270:12"/>and taſte, according to their ſeuerall likings. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their arriuall, ſhee would ſeem to be at large expence for their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement, ſpreading her banquets in euery ſtreete, in euery houſe, in euery chamber, where ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints them with her bed, deckt with orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, carpets, and laces of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and perfumed with Myrrhe, Aloes, and Cynamon, <hi>Prou.</hi> 7.16. that after they haue ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited at board, her profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red medeale may bee the better accepted, which is thus compounded; <hi>Come
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:181270:13"/>let vs take our fill of loue till the morning.</hi> A pill ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid with Gold; but of this vertue to purge the ſoule from pietie, and the purſſe from plentie. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhe hath nothing, whereof to ſhew choiſe to her cuſtomers, but a packe of odious ſinnes, and thoſe of vnſpeakable varietie; and therefore is tearmed <hi>Malorum eſca, the baite of Euils,</hi> which who ſo deuoureth, ſhall bee ſurely caught, and drawne into a maze of impieties, to lay ſinne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſinne, luxury vpon gluttony, pride vpon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:181270:13"/>irreligion vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſecuritie, till neither line vpon line, nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept vpon precept can help him out, but he ſinke farther into a gulfe of ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reparable miſeries. That certaine rich man, (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werthy to haue his name mentioned in the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, which was neuer to be inſerted in the booke of life) ſwallowed her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day in his delicious dier, put her on daily in his ſumptuous apparrell, and daily lockt her vp in his glittering coffers: and this ſo benummed his heart, againſt all ſenſe of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:181270:14"/>grace, mercie, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that for the ſame cauſe, after death, being in hell, it was told him from heauen: <hi>Thou art tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Luke</hi> 16.25. and that ſo, as no man could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire vnto him with ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of relaxation, or preſent comfort.</p>
                  <p>The forme of <hi>Pleaſures</hi> Common-weale, is <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mecraticall:</hi> and whereas <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> conſtitutes foure kinds of <hi>Democraties,</hi> this of hers is the laſt, and very worſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where euery one liueth as he liſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, without reſpecting or regarding the Lawes,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:181270:14"/>and Magiſtrates; and as he ſaith of that, ſo is the adminiſtration of this ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall, through her ſlatteries &amp; perſwaſions: the Kings Guard is of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, the Tyrants of Strangers Pleaſure is not guarded with vertues, which are ciuill &amp; prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but with vices, which are barbarous, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine: by whom ſhee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth to ſubdue and yoake vertue, that it may beare no ſway, nor make any ſhew among them: or elſe to put it to vtter exile, that without feare of oppoſition, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:181270:15"/>ſhe may rule and domineere as ſhee will; hence is that truth of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero. In voluptatis regno, non poteſt virtus conſiſtere. Vertue can make no quiet reſidence in the Territories of Pleaſure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt authorizing his Diſciples to goe abroad into the world, &amp; preach, ſaid; <hi>I ſend you as ſheepe among Wolues:</hi> In the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of which his Mitto, he (as it were) paints the World, with an open mouth, roaring at pietie, and euer ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the profeſſors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: neither did they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:181270:15"/>their office, onely with long hazzard, but at length, to the loſſe of their liues; Thoſe earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirits, that draw breath in darkneſſe, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure the ſacred ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine to detect their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualities. The auaritious Phariſes, heard Chriſt reproue Couetouſneſſe, and they mocked him, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.14. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſought to make peace betweene two <hi>Hebrews</hi> that ſtroue, &amp; he that did the wrong, reproachfully tanted him, <hi>Who made thee a man of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and a Iudge ouer vs? Exod.</hi> 2.14. When the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:181270:16"/>blinde man reſtored to ſight, confeſſed Chriſt to the faithleſſe <hi>Iewes,</hi> they caſt him out with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, <hi>Thou art alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether borne in ſinne, and doeſt thou teach vs? Iohn</hi> 9.34. Religion ſuffers many a ſharpe repulſe, by them that are the Proctors of Pleaſure, to pleade for her ſinnes: they remoue it fartheſt from the heart, and reſolue to haue no encounter with it; If it be a doctrine of renouation, and new birth, without which no man can ſee God, they reiect it out of ignorant admiration, as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:181270:16"/>a thing impoſſible, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Nicodemus, How can a man be borne when he is old? Iohn</hi> 2.4. If of diuine worſhip and holy duties, then auerſly with <hi>Gallio. Iudices nos horum nolumus eſſe: We will be no Iudges of theſe things, Act.</hi> 18.15. They are ſo infatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated with the cup of her ſorceries, that (as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant chooſeth a Rattle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a wedge of Gold) they runne affectionately after her featherie toyes, and caſt off heauenly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: ſo eluded with her impoſtures, that they can diſcerne nothing in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:181270:17"/>true colour and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from whence they confound <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> ſinne with <hi>Sanctimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> looſing the ſenſe of grace, the horror of their ſinnes, the deſire of things eternall, the feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments infernall, euen by that neere and arct coniunction they haue with corporall delights. <hi>The natural man perceiueth not the things that are of God, for they are fooliſhneſſe vnto him.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſaid in my heart</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Preacher) Goe to now, I will proue thee with toy, therefore take thou plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:181270:17"/>in pleaſant things, and behold this alſo is vanitie. I ſaid of laughter, thou art mad: and of ioy, what is this that thou doeſt? Eccleſ.</hi> 2.1.2. He did heere but purpoſe this courſe to himſelfe, which after hee had conſiderately diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>reputauit errorem,</hi> he concluded to be ſo erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and ſo meerely vaine, that it was not worth the vndertaking: yet afterward, hee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held not his eies from whatſoeuer they deſired, nor withdrew his heart from any ioy: and when he had looked on all his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:181270:18"/>workes, and on all his trauell, this was the ſum againe, <hi>Behold, all is vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and vexation of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> So that if any <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> diſtracted too farre with the concupiſcence of deceitfull ioyes, ſhall ſeeme to challenge his iudgement in the firſt, it will bee ſafe for him to credit his experience at the laſt, and not venture on ſo ſlender a bridge, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer an horrible <hi>abyſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Immoderate laughter ſtirred vp by outward aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects &amp; occaſions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Chriſtian ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, which ſhould ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:181270:18"/>our behauiour, is more then reputed madneſſe, and ſuch ioy makes vs ſeeme to do we know not what. As well might <hi>Sampſon</hi> haue ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the crueltie of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> when they put out his eyes, &amp;c. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16. as we in thoſe tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, which by the fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our hearts vpon them, obcecate our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the breeders of our confuſion: and <hi>Saul</hi> as wel when he tooke his ſword in his hand where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he ſlew himſelfe; we take hold of vanitie,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:181270:19"/>and falſhood a refuge, which pierce the ſoule with anxious cares, and wound it to the ſecond death; and what is it for vs to triumph in theſe things?</p>
                  <p>Chriſt himſelfe choſe the hardeſt part, a part full of aſperitie, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe, as it is noted from the euidence of his manifold pouertie, and the abſence of all terrene pleaſures, in his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, in his death, and by that meanes entred into his glorie; whoſe whole life was to vs, <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplina morum,</hi> that wee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:181270:19"/>ſhould imitate him, in moralitie <hi>Moſes</hi> concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued no matter of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in the pleaſures of ſinne, therefore accepted rather to ſuffer affliction with the godly: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Saints wandred vp and downe, in Sheepe skinnes, and in Goates skinnes, <hi>Egentes anguſtati, afflicti, deſtitute, beſtreigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, afflicted, Heb.</hi> 11.37. And all theſe through faith obtained good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, ver. 39. But the Princes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> then waxed careleſſe of requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite vertues: then forgate to ſorrow for the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:181270:20"/>of their brethren, and then loathed the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of godly aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, when they betooke themſelues to eaſe, to fare daintily, to the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Wine, to Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, and ſinging, <hi>Amos</hi> 6. So when we are wrapt in this ſupputed heauen, which wee are ſeldome out of: we ſay, of laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, thou art grace; and of ioy, thou art the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſolace: looking to the ſoules health through theſe pleaſures, as at a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote obiect through a proſpectiue glaſſe, which makes it to bee thought
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:181270:20"/>neere, being in truth, far off: whilſt wee miſtake theſe groſſe, and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing miſts, to be <hi>pelluci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Coelum,</hi> as if we were then in <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, when we are in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans bondage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> and his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſociates, when they were in carouſing of wine, praiſed their gods of Siluer and Gold, &amp;c. ſuppoſing there was ſome vertue in them to do them good: but what ſaw <hi>Belſhazzar?</hi> Found he not a God aboue all his gods, that did anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilate their power, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:181270:21"/>fruſtrate his owne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation? He ſaw an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition, and was it not a little one? It was but a hand, but it was ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen; and was it not a mightie one? His heart was hautie, and his limbs luſtie, yet could hee not behold it, without the fainting of the one, and the feebleneſſe of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: before he knew the true meaning of it, his countenance was chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and his thoughts troubled him, a ſad pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of a fearefull conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; he diſhonoured his Creator, and did glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:181270:21"/>in the Creature, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was hee degraded from his honour, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from his kingdome, and depriued of his life, for he was to light.</p>
                  <p>As it cannot be (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) that fire ſhould flame in Water: ſo neither can the heart labour of compunction for ſinne, when it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp, and made inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible with pleaſure: for theſe are repugnant one to the other; <hi>Illa enim ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſt fletus, haec mater eſt riſus, illa cor conſtringit, iſta diſſoluit; Becauſe that is the mother of lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:181270:22"/>this of lightneſſe, that compoſeth, and ſettles the heart, this diſſolues, and diſorders it.</hi> It makes vs laud the gods of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, as if they were po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull to deliuer vs, and contemne the Authour, and finiſher of our faith, as if the Storie of his mercie, power, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, were but a fable. In quaffing we extoll <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> take him for our high Prieſt, and pay him tenth vpon our knees, <hi>Alij ſtantes, diſcumbentes alij, omnes ex animo</hi> which way ſoeuer, all do it with all their hearts: in ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:181270:22"/>to <hi>Epicurus;</hi> in Muſicke, to <hi>Apollo,</hi> wee ſweare all allegiance; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no more ſtay of our affections, nor ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of fidelitie, then to become ſeruants vnto al, that wil ſerue vs but with a fit of ſlippery content. The finger of the Holy Ghoſt hath written our iudgement, wee haue read it, we haue heard it, but are no whit changed, nor abaſhed. Chriſt hath ſpoken as it were from heauen, to euery one of vs, with that voice that came to <hi>Saul, Why deeſt thou perſecute me?</hi> But we
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:181270:23"/>neither tremble, nor aske what wilt thou Lord that we ſhall doe? Wee are more braſen, then timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> more impudent then tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Foelix,</hi> more obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate then halfe perſwaded <hi>Agrippa,</hi> whom no inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues againſt ſinne, no lift vp voyce of any Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er on earth, no iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments exemplified from aboue, no terrors concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from beneath, can truly conuert to true Chriſtianitie: <hi>When I ſaw</hi> (ſaith Iehouah) <hi>how that by all occaſions rebellious Iſrael had plaied the harlot,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:181270:23"/>I caſt her away, and gaue her a bill of diuorcement: yet her rebellious Siſter Iudah was not afraid, but ſhee went alſo and played the harlot, Ier.</hi> 3.8. After both their backſlidings in fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful rebellion, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation towards them, we alſo a litle Siſter vnto them, <hi>Can.</hi> 8.8. come on careleſſe, feareleſſe, and commit fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with our pleaſures. It is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> that for his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſobriety and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, hee was the onely mirrour of <hi>Italy,</hi> who by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:181270:24"/>ouercomming himſelfe, ouercame all Europe; A worthy precedent for the imitation of Greatneſſe, who are to know, that <hi>Parui ſunt foris arma, niſi eſt conſilium domi.</hi> To maſter our little world, is the firſt ſtep to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the whole world; albeit they meane not to contend for Countries, <hi>vi, &amp; armis,</hi> yet are they bound to endeauour <hi>vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, &amp; abſtinentia,</hi> to that chriſtian fortitude, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by not to feare what man can doe vnto them. Let <hi>Temperance</hi> keepe the doore of the ſtomacke,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:181270:24"/>and exclude ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the foule ſpirit, ſhall finde no place of habitation in the heart, whereby to ſubiect it to worldly feares: for that which is <hi>recti iudicij te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nax, doctrinae capax, bonae famae ſemper auida, ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria atque vtilia creans,</hi> as is Temperance, of a right and orderly iudgement, of an able capacitie for doctrine, couetous of a good report, creating profitable and wholſome <hi>Theorems</hi> in the ſoule, is to well reſolued, and to heauenly affected, to let in ſo hoſtile a gueſt, ſo
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:181270:25"/>dangerous a truce-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker betweene God and Man. <hi>Daniel,</hi> that hee might not be entiſed to forget his Religion, and accuſtomed ſobriety (for ſo was the Kings purpoſe in appointing him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of his owne coſtly fare) determined in his heart, that he would not defile himſelfe therwith, but eate pulſe, and drank water, being a certaine preſeruatiue for them both; for ſo <hi>Origen</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth, that <hi>ſobrietie is the mother of all vertues;</hi> and Saint <hi>Auſtine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 1.8.12.</note> 
                     <hi>Eſt virtutis ſingulare auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:181270:25"/>cuncta cum ratione diſponens: It is a ſingular ayde to vertue, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all things with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> For which cauſe could not the moſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome by the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of the Noble <hi>Thraſians,</hi> to taſte of their prepared dainties; hee fed onely on their bread and drinke, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Foote-men and ſlaues, to feede if they would vpon ſuch cheere, for that (hee ſaid) Princes might not pamper themſelues, with delicate cheere,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:181270:26"/>and Wines, but vſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, &amp; temperance; the one being vicious and ſhamefull; the other a free Nurſe to vertue and Fame. He reſpecting himſelfe as (hee was) a King turned ouer this pleaſure, as a ſordide and ſlauiſh exerciſe to his meaneſt ſeruants, leaſt vſing it himſelfe, hee might through forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, haue become as infamous as the worſt of them, hauing loſt that Iewell, which is of beſt note, and moſt valuable, in the Diadem of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:181270:26"/>
                  <p>So did <hi>Eliah,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> nouriſh the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by Prayer, and abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence:
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.4.</note> his meate was no fleſh, neither dranke hee Wine, nor ſtrong drink, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.15. The other was contented with bread, and fleſh as the Rauens brought it him morning and euening, and dranke of the riuer. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 17.6. <hi>Woe bee to thee, O Land, when thy King is a Childe, and thy Princes</hi> (meaning Magiſtrates and Rulers) <hi>eate in the morning, (that is) intemperatly, for ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting, &amp; not for ſtrength. Prou.</hi> 10.16. In this ſenſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:181270:27"/>ſpake Queene <hi>Bethſheba,</hi> to her Sonne King <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: It is not good for Kings O Lemuell,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 31.4.5</note> 
                     <hi>it is not good for Kings to drinke wine, nor for Princes ſtrong drinke, leaſt he drinke and forget the decree, and change the iudgement of all the children of affliction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We may ſtay our eies at home, vpon our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and ſacred <hi>Lemuel,</hi> who hath (as vprightly as euer any) obeyed the voyce of wiſedome his Mother, to eate her meate, and drinke the Wine that ſhee hath drawne, <hi>Prou.</hi> 9.5. And
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:181270:27"/>publiſhed the fruits ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to the incomparable comfort, and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his people, feeding them with a faithfull and true heart, and ruling them prudently with all his power, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.73. of whom all our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> impartially confeſſeth, They haue heard the iudgement which the King hath iudged, and they feare the King, for they ſee the wiſedome of God is in him to doe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 2.28.</p>
                  <p>Would the Starres of our Sphere, I meane not the ſixed, but the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:181270:28"/>ones, take luſtre from this Sunne, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering themſelues to be eyes of a maigne bodie, through whom it ſhould ſee to walke ſafely: neuer would ſo many ſtumble at their vices, lying in the way, as hauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to excuſe it withal, but want of light. It were not credible, that the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant would ſmoake his flitches, with his Maſters <hi>Indian</hi> fuell, and after bathe them in the fooliſh forfeiture of his wits, till he farther ieopard his ſaluation, by the heede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe aggrauating of hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:181270:28"/>oathes, in his ſight and hearing; were ſuch commaunders any better then darke Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thornes, which ſhine not backe to thoſe that follow them. How cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe they caſt off, not onely the deſert of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed dignitie of Men, ſeeing that, <hi>Nemo eſt dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus nomine hominis, qui vnum diem totum, velit eſſe in voluptate. He is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be called a Man, that will waſte one whole day in pleaſure.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> rendereth a ſtrict and vnanſwerable reaſon, in telling vs the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:181270:29"/>end of all things is at hand; and therefore wee muſt be ſober, and watch in prayer. There is no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance permitted vnto vs, for the looſing any time, in offenſiue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: for then is there no hope that we ſhall ſtand in the iudgement
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note>, or quit our ſelues like men, if we neglect to prepare our ſoules, with thoſe commanded Graces (ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie and Prayer) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the comming of the Lord; and yet is a day but a minute, that is, but a moment, that as nothing with them that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:181270:29"/>will make to morrow as this day, and much more abundant, crying out after delight as the ſluggard for his ſleepe, yet a little more, ſo hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out their progreſſe. <hi>Vntill the ſtrong men bow themſelues, and the grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ceaſe, and the duſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the earth as it was. Eccleſ.</hi> 11.13.</p>
                  <p>It was the demaund of the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> to <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> a Prince of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Iehoſhua,</hi> the high Prieſt, concerning the Temple of the Lord. <hi>Is it time for your ſelues to dwell in your ſealed houſes,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:181270:30"/>and this houſe lye waſte?</hi> The pleaſure taken in ſtately edifices, is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times enough to drowne the care of Gods ſeruice: they being now become (as in the olde world) holes of Cockatrices, and teguments of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, where out ſeldome creepes a vertue, for want of grace within, to giue it liuelihood &amp; ſtrength; ranck prouender growes about them plentifully: but <hi>latet anguis in herbis,</hi> it is not gathered, nor ſpent, without ſinne and ſhame. Chriſts impotent members lye begging of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:181270:30"/>the crums, (which Chriſt in his own perſon vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed from the Table of his mercy, to the Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitiſh Dogge) but there is no man to giue vnto them, for (as Saint <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> truly) <hi>Cor habet in ventre guloſus, laſciuius in libidine, cupidus in lucro;</hi> The glutton hath ſuch a mind on his belly, the wanton on his luſt, and the auarous on his gaine, that by that time the Cormorant hath ſpent all, in feeding his luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous appetite, and the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous ſpared all, to the conſumption of his own
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:181270:31"/>carkaſes; the poore may depart emptie as they came, bearing in their hunger bitten cheekes, and deiected Spirits, an example of that approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued rule; <hi>Semper eris pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſi pauper es.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <l>If (wretched ſoule)</l>
                  <l>thou liu'ſt in need,</l>
                  <l>The richer ſort</l>
                  <l>will let thee bleed:</l>
                  <l>The Dogs may lecke</l>
                  <l>thy ſmarting ſores,</l>
                  <l>But pittie none,</l>
                  <l>peeps out of doores.</l>
                  <p>Somtimes the pretence of Iuſtice, in obſeruing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:181270:31"/>the Statutes, is a barre to their deuotion: but Oh! vniuſt crueltie, when as their loue to true Iuſtice indeede, is nothing leſſe then they would heerein praiſe it to be: Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence proclaiming ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther right deplorable cauſe thereof to be. <hi>Nil tamen attuleris, &amp;c.</hi> For gifts blind the eies of the wiſe: yet ſo, that they will neuer ſee to vndertake the indigent, till they haue thus put them out.</p>
                  <p>Gods houſe cals vpon ſuch pompeous Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords for tribute, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire her ruines: but they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:181270:32"/>haue ſo many euils, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, faſhions, conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, deformities, lie nib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at their bagges, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for maintenance, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> cannot haue his due, neither can they ſpare ought to the honor of God; whereas to the former,</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Noctes, atque dies,</l>
                        <l>patet atri ianui Ditis.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Their bags, the mouth</l>
                        <l>of Plutoes ſable caue</l>
                        <l>Which beare this thirſty</l>
                        <l>Motto (ſtill we craue;)</l>
                        <l>Lye euer open, to the</l>
                        <l>hand of ſinne,</l>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:181270:32"/>
                        <l>Where Grace in vaine,</l>
                        <l>petitions to come in.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>It ſhall neither mooue them to paſſion nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, to pitty, nor pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to ſee the gates of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (which the Lord ſo highly preferreth) to lye waſte. Againe, this San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary opens her doore that the King of glorie (according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe) may come in, when his ſeruants ſhall repaire to that place where hee hath put his Name, to do him worſhip. But heere is found vſually, as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of a great many,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:181270:33"/>ſo not of many great: whereof ſome reſt ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with a few typid pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of their owne at home, being onely a morning ſacrifice for the whole day: and offered vp in a Cloſet, without any teſtimony, but of their owne conſciences, that is enough to free them of hypocriſie, and (as they are perſwaded) to obtain remiſſion here, and a reward in heauen. Others heare them from other men, but without a mentall conſent, or ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the heart, as the ſequell of their behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:181270:33"/>ſhamefully confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; neither of them, loues a fiery zeale: for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting a carnall proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, they cannot beare, to bee eaten vp with the zeale of Gods houſe. Howbeit the Church ſtands not as a Rocke in the Sea, to bee auoyded, but as a Cliffe on the ſhoare, to ſhew vs that thither we ſhould direct our courſe. Neither did the people of God in their baniſhment, vow the prelation of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem to their chiefeſt ioy, but that they were there moſt happy, where they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:181270:34"/>could freely ſerue the Lord. For all this they hauing builded their ſumptuous houſes, by the might of their power, &amp; for their honour, (as proudly ſaid <hi>Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi>) they reſolue it is time for them, wholy to repoſe in theſe, and leaue their rooms in the Lords houſe empty.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Adamites</hi> were a Sect, whoſe cuſtome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty is loath to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But they deuiſed them a Church after an hot-houſe; for the ſpace of ſeruice time, they went all naked, Men and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:181270:34"/>Women, and the virgins preached vnto the reſt. Are not ſuch houſes, made (if I may ſo ſay) our moſt frequented Churches? Or I would ſuch Preachers were not moſt reuerenced, &amp; beſt beloued. Beeing with them, our <hi>Adamites</hi> (as thoſe other) iudge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in Paradiſe; one word diſtilling from the tongue of ſuch an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe, gaines ſoules and bodies to her ſeruice, more then many vigilant Diuines can ouercome to God. The Arke of the Lord was accounted the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:181270:35"/>glory of Iſrael; <hi>The glory is departed from Iſrael, for the Arke of God is taken.</hi> 1. Sam. 4.22. But we like Gentiles of vncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hearts, doe not ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of his Temple, but caſt vp our accounts another waies, and goe a whoring after heatheniſh abominations: yet not imagining a Queene of Heauen, but imagining an earthly Miſtreſſe to worſhip her: who works a ſtranger effect with her flexible audience, then Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> long Sermon did with <hi>Eutichus:</hi> he fell downe in a ſleepe, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:181270:35"/>was taken vp dead: Act. 20.9. notwithſtanding his heauenly doctrine: but they, if halfe dead, are by her mortall incan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, throughly quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and reuiued.</p>
                  <p>This is a pleaſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued partly in the eye; and for that the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers condemne our choice; ſaying, it is <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarius, &amp; homine dignius, Coelum potius quam coelata intueri, &amp; hoc pulcherri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum opus (inter micanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aſtrorum luminibus tanquam floribus adorna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum) quam ficta, &amp; picta, &amp; gemmis diſtincta mirars:</hi>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:181270:36"/>More excellent and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a Man, to behold the Heauens, then any thing faſhioned, and ſet forth by the art of Man: and rather to admire the beauty of that fabricke, graced with luminous Lamps (to put vs in mind of our Creator, of our calling, of our Country, that the firſt is God, and not Man: ſecondly, that we being chriſtians, haue laſtly not Earth, but Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for our Country) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as the ſenſe may fairely beare it) wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (in reſpect of their monſtrous, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth diſguiſments, feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned)
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:181270:36"/>painted, and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Iewels.</p>
                  <p>It hath alſo its concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; partly in the eare, by reaſon of effeminate adulation, and bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blandiſhments: for (as <hi>Lactantius</hi> aply) <hi>Oratio cum ſuauitate decipiens ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit mentes, &amp; quo voluerit impellit:</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>Speech ſweetly ſeaſon'd,</l>
                        <l>doth intrap mens minds,</l>
                        <l>And as it liſt ſeduce,</l>
                        <l>in ſundry kinds.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And foraſmuch as ſuch pellacious charmes, doe vndoubtedly draw them to a diſlike, &amp; aſpernation of the ſimple ſpeech of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:181270:37"/>the Goſpell of Chriſt, and are <hi>irratamenta vitto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quae ad corrumpendos animos potiſsime valent;</hi> the ſpurs of vices which mghtily preuaile to the corruption, and depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of our ſoules, it is needfull to conclude with the Author of theſe words, <hi>Ergo tollenda ſunt nobis,</hi> We muſt therefore void, abandon, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce them.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:181270:37"/>
                     <head>WHAT, AND HOW FARRE PLEASVRES ARE lawfull, and to be vſed.</head>
                     <p>ALbeit affliction was dictated by Chriſt to his Diſciples, &amp; through them to all the faithfull, for the very portion, which they are to expect and receiue from the World, in this world: yet was it not with an abſolute inhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:181270:38"/>of all outward plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or any full excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on taken thereunto; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meant onely ſo much as was neceſſaty for them becauſe it is a Point in Chriſts Church, that <hi>through many tribulations they muſt enter into the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> And the godly haue beene ſomtimes excited by the Prophets, from God himſelfe, to reioyce, in regard he would remoue this grieuance from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in ſtead of affliction, caſt out their enemies, giuing them reſt, and a releaſe from his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:181270:38"/>
                        <hi>Reioyce, O Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sion, be ioyfull, O Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, be glad, and reioyce with all thy heart, O Daughter Hieruſalem; the Lord hath taken away thy iudgements, he hath caſt out thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Zep.</hi> 3.14.15.</p>
                     <p>The Preachers compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue poſition; <hi>It is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to enter into the houſe of mourning, then into the houſe of feaſting,</hi> doth not ouerthrow our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of ſome recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: it proouing chiefely the preſtantio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of mourning, as it ſerueth to expreſſe the mortification of our
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:181270:39"/>members that are on earth; and the inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of inordinate fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, as it is the vſuall brother of euill concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence.</p>
                     <p>There is a two-fold ioy lawfull, and granted: 1. The one a meere out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ioy: riſing either from the beneficiall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and conſtitution of Nature, of which, <hi>Prou.</hi> 17.22. <hi>A ioyfull heart cauſeth good health:</hi> by this meanes doe ſome lightly ouerpaſſe croſſes, and accidents of trouble, with ſmal imparagement to their health and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:181270:39"/>which doe melt and conſume the hearts of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. This then is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for the occaſioning and conſeruation of health: to the recupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and maintenance whereof, vpon the fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or deficiency of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is alſo commended vnto vs, the vſe of Oyle, and Wine, and Bread, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.23. and vnder them, of all Creatures that may profit to this purpoſe. <hi>Zibah</hi> met <hi>Dauid</hi> flying from <hi>Abſalom,</hi> with two Aſſes, laden with proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, &amp; a bottle of wine,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:181270:40"/>that the faint might drinke in the wilderneſſe. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.1.2. <hi>Wine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth the liuing,</hi> Eccleſ. 10.19. <hi>Should I leaue my Wine</hi> (ſaid the Vine) <hi>wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I cheere God, and Man, and goe to aduance mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the trees. Iud.</hi> 9.13. And thus farre it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by God for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to them that loue him. <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.14. But the loue of theſe which cauſeth exceſſe, is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with woe. <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.11. and with pouertie, <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 21.17. Now health is neceſſarie to our prompt and alacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:181270:40"/>ſeruing of GOD; for, by the ſorrow of the heart, the minde is heauy. <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 15.13. and ſuch deiection, doth forcibly ſuppreſſe good, &amp; comfortable thoughts and actions.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Or elſe from thoſe materiall and externall bleſſings, which God hath conferred vpon vs graunted, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.12.13. I know there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, and to do good in his life, and alſo, that euery man eateth and drinketh and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the commoditie
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:181270:41"/>of all his labours, this is the gift of God. And Chap. 5.17. What haue I ſeene good, that it is comly, to eate and drink, and to take pleaſure in all his labour, wherein hee trauelleth vnder the Sun, the whole number of the daies of his life, which God giueth him; for this is his portion.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The other is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ioy, reſpecting Gods promiſes, touching protection and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in the militarie courſe of this life, and a future indeficient felicity in the next: and therein
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:181270:41"/>is not tyed in the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy, to our weak, fraile, and changeable bodyes; but howſoeuer they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, and languiſh, this remaineth immutably the ſame, in reſpect of ioy: but yet is capable of increaſe, for that, it comes not to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, till this mortall hath put on immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<note place="margin">The ſeat of this ioy.</note> It is properly ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſoule, there begunne, cheriſhed, and confirmed by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable preſence of the Spirit of God.
<note place="margin">To whom it belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> It is the ioy of true beleeuers onely, <hi>Eſt gaudium, quod
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:181270:42"/>non datur impijs.</hi> It is not communicable to the impious and vngodly. It ſerues to moderate that other externall ioy,
<note place="margin">The vſe of it.</note> that it exceede not due mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and to direct it, that it point not at a wrong end.
<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of it.</note> 
                        <hi>Eſt gaudium ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, quod non abſcondi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, nec ſermonibus aperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi> It cannot be verbally expreſſed, for the extent and excellency, yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be concealed, but <hi>quibuſaam proditur moribus,</hi> (as Saint <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>) it is manifeſted by outward ſignes and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures. Whereof ſome
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:181270:42"/>are recreating the body, as <hi>Dauids</hi> dancing before the Arke of the Lord, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.14. and <hi>Miri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> dauncing with other Women, to ſignifie their great ioy after their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.20. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers onely ſolacing the mind, as ſinging, and playing on Inſtruments, to the praiſe of God. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 150. So ſang <hi>Deborah</hi> &amp; <hi>Barak,</hi> after their victory atchieued againſt <hi>Iabin,</hi> King of <hi>Canaan. Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> ſung a Pſalme in the priſon, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.25. It is alſo teſtified, ſometimes by other behauiour, as
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:181270:43"/>by that of <hi>Zaccheus,</hi> when he came downe, vnto Chriſt haſtily, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him ioyfully, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.6. by that of <hi>Marie Magdalen,</hi> and the other <hi>Marie,</hi> who declared their ioy, when Ieſus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Reſurrection ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto them, in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him by the feet, and worſhipping him, <hi>Math.</hi> 28.9. Here is an <hi>Eden</hi> of Pleaſure able to giue a plentifull ſatisfaction, to the mind of any ſincere Chriſtian. We are not denied a ſober and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent delight, in any temporals wee haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:181270:43"/>and touching the internall releuating of the Spirit, we are exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to reioyce more then it is poſſible for any worldling to doe, that is
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.16.</note> euermore. Whence is obiected the ſound, and permanent qualitie of this ioy, that is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any Eclipſe, or deminution through ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie; and moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer preuailes to the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and eaſie ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of all tribulation. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with this ioy, ſpake indifferently of all conditions, diſreſpect,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:181270:44"/>and honour, ſatiety, and hunger; ſcarſity and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, were to him alike; the one neither af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected him with pride, nor the other with pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiueneſſe, but he embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them all, with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall good content, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in euery of them he held the peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and a reioycing in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                     <p>Who alſo witneſſeth of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that they receiued the word of God in much afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with ioy of the holy Ghoſt. It was ſuch as did not onely prepare them,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:181270:44"/>to a voluntary &amp; cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vndergoing, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them alſo, to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſupporting, and bearing of the Croſſe for Chriſts ſake and his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels. Therefore hauing ſtraightly prohibited all vaine-glory, in wiſdome, in ſtrength, in riches; <hi>Let him that glorieth, glory in this, that he knoweth and vnderſtandeth mee, ſaith the Lord, Iſa.</hi> 9.23. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in the Lord, againe I ſay reioyce, Phil.</hi> 4.4. For this ioy is of Chriſt, and exhibited by Chriſt, and no Man ſhall take it from the faithfull, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.22.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:181270:45"/>It onely leanes to a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt &amp; infallible ground, which is our Adoption, the Redemption of our bodies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. Or that, <hi>Wee ſhall be cloathed with our houſe which is from heauen,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. that ſo being changed we may for euer, with thouſand thouſands of Angels, <hi>Aſcribe vnto the Lambe, honour and glorie, and praiſe, Reuel.</hi> 5.12. Wherefore when the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle wils vs to runne: and Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, <hi>Curramus &amp; ſequamur Chriſtum, Let vs runne and follow Chriſt.</hi> Wee are
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:181270:45"/>taught concerning this World, that we muſt vſe it, as if we vſed it not, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31. So that, if there be in vs any zeale, or fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent deſire of labouring, wee are to addreſſe our ſelues therein, toward heauen, by ſetting our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection on things which are aboue, <hi>Colloſſ.</hi> 3.2. for <hi>non ſunt hic vera ſolatia, ſed ibi ponuntur, vbi vera vita eſt.</hi> Heere is no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted comfort to bee found, (therefore is our labour loſt, when inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to that, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be compaſſed) but there is the ſweet refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:181270:46"/>the ſetled conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the abiding ioy where Chriſt euer reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and life neuer end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: <hi>Illud eſt verum, &amp; ſummum gaudium, quod non de creatura, ſed de cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atore concipitur,</hi> (as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſweetly) the cheefe, and ſole ioy, and the ſum of al ioyes, is that we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of our Creator; in compariſon whereof, all our pleaſure is but care, our contentation no better then vexation, all ſweetneſſe bitter, and whatſoeuer delights vs, is but troubleſome.</p>
                     <p>We can build nothing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:181270:46"/>in the fleſh but ruine, nor reape ought beſides cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneum eſt quod delectat, ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum quod cruciat:</hi> the flaſhing pleaſures of the fleſh are extiguiſhed with infinite, eaſleſſe and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe paines: (whereas in the kingdome of Grace, with the Saints of God it is otherwiſe: <hi>Momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum quod cruciat, aeternu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod delectat: Their light afflictions, which are but for a moment do cauſe vnto them a far moſt excellent &amp; eternall weight of glory.</hi>) Fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Ephraim</hi> any honor in her pride? any aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:181270:47"/>in her drunkenneſſe? Or that <hi>Babylon</hi> of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and fleſhly whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, hath ſhe carryed away any Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation by her idoll ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice (as they tearme it) and cautelous proſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Or the raging Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then any victory, by combining themſelues in a conſpiracy againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt? They made a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant with death, and with Hell they are at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15. Yet doe they from hence vainely indulge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with a confidence
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:181270:47"/>of impunity: for Chriſt hauing purchaſed a vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal Lordſhip ouer the quicke and the dead, by dying and riſing againe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. exactly challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a proportionable fealtie, that all knees ſhal bow before him, and all tongues confeſſe him; <hi>And they that prouoke him ſhall be aſhamed,</hi> Iſa. 45.23.24. It is an aduenture as hopefull, to ſaile to the golden Mines of <hi>Peru</hi> in a Ship of Glaſſe, as that we in pride, in couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in pleaſures, may haue a welcome acceſſe to God, <hi>in die nouiſsimo,</hi>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:181270:48"/>that great, new, and laſt day, &amp; ſo enter the ſweet <hi>Elyſium</hi> of heauenly reſt. For as, when the children of <hi>Benianim,</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> went to helpe <hi>Dauid,</hi> he ſaid vnto them; <hi>If ye bee come peaceably, my heart ſhall be knit vnto you; but if otherwiſe God behold it, and rebuke it,</hi> 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.17: So if we will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God, to fight his battails vnder the tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne banner, we muſt make a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble repaire vnto him, with the ſpirit of meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, obedience, &amp; loue, and not with the ſignes
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:181270:48"/>of hoſtility, and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as are thoſe ſinnes, wherein the wiſedome of the fleſh doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and animate vs: for that being enmity againſt God, ſuggeſteth vnto vs nothing, but to be ſtubborne, to rebell, and ſtand out in our own conceits, and not ſubmit our ſelues to the yoake of Chriſt: and ſo long can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not he knit his heart vnto vs, nor behold vs, but as an incorrupted Iudge, with due auſteritie to reprooue and reiect vs: for his owne hand is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all our iniquities;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:181270:49"/>therefore vnleſſe we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and forſake them, they may not be cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. It was <hi>Darius</hi> his caſe, who after hee had ſealed the writing againſt them, which ſhould aske any petition of any God or Man for thirtie dayes ſaue of himſelfe; when <hi>Daniel</hi> was accuſed that he regarded him not; he could not deliuer him though hee laboured till the Sunne went downe. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.14. How then ſhall God be inconſtant in his word and purpoſe, in whom there is no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie of mutation?</p>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:181270:49"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The faſhion of this world paſſeth away.</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31.) So that by vniting our harts to things tranſitory, wee baſely confine our hope to a period of time, to the moment of death: <hi>When the wicked man dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, his hope periſheth, Pro.</hi> 11. hauing no waies to ſend it vp, paſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of deſpicable and dying Obiects, to the Throne of heauen, there to releeue &amp; ſtrengthen it, with a certaine appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of eternity: but our ſubmiſſe relying on Chriſt, as a ſure ſounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:181270:50"/>is whoſe feare is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured ſtrength. <hi>Prou.</hi> 14. It is a good hope, and an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting conſolation, which leſus Chriſt that loued vs, hath giuen vnto vs.</p>
                     <p>Neuertheleſſe, wicked men, whoſe waies for the moſt part proſper (as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> noteth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.) contemne God, and ſay in their hearts, they ſhall neuer be moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, nor be in danger: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing vnto themſelues a perpetuity of perfect bleſſedneſſe from thoſe vnſtable adminicles, which God hath curſed
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:181270:50"/>vnto them: how they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult we ſee; who bear rule? who command? who are obeied? Who feared ſo much as they? they prate and ſpeake fearefully, <hi>All the workers of iniquitie vant themſelues, they ſmite thy people, O Lord, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thine heritage, Pſal.</hi> 94.45. We ſhall not haue a good Chriſtian triumph in the deceitfulneſſe of things preſent, here being no Theatre of exultation for them, but a vale of mourning, a bryerie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, &amp; a warring pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, who are hereafter freed from all infirmities
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:181270:51"/>and miſeries, to bee go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by the Lambe, who ſhall leade them to the liuely fountaines of waters: <hi>And God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes, Apoc.</hi> 7.17. So that the impious boaſters are only to expect a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and deſperate end; whom if God were not determined moſt ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and incogitably to torture in flaming fire, <hi>Rendring vengeance vnto them,</hi> 2. Theſſ. 1.8. <hi>When he ſhall iudge the ſecrets of men by Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Rom. 2.16. He would not now permit to tranſgreſſe, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:181270:51"/>prouoke him as they do: but for his greater glory, in the manifeſtation of his hyeſt Iuſtice, doth he ſuffer them in this life, to make full the meaſure of their impieties, that hee may diſcharge the full vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of his wrath, vpon their odious ſoules at laſt; giuing to euery <hi>quantum</hi> of ſcandalous pleaſure, a <hi>tantum</hi> of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable torment. Hell hath enlarged it ſelfe, and hath opened its mouth without meaſure (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>) for them that royne houſe to houſe, and field to field;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:181270:52"/>for them that riſe vp ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to follow drunkennes: and for them that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue vntill night, till the wine doe inflame them: and haue the Harpe and Violl, Timbrell &amp; Pipe, and wine, in their feaſts: but they regard not the worke of the Lord; their glory, and their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and their pompe, and he that reioyceth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, ſhal deſcend into it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.14. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> preſents them as it were ſtanding at Gods Tribunall, where what he ſaw in the Spirit, reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, concerning ſuch, he
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:181270:52"/>reuealeth thus againe; <hi>I beheld, and loe the Kings of the earth, and the great men, and the rich men, and the chiefe Captaines, and the mightie men, and euery bond man, and euery free man,</hi> (being vngodly and diſobedient) <hi>hid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in dens, and in the Rockes of the mountaines, and ſaid to the Mountaines and Rockes, fall on vs, and hide vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preſence of him that ſitteth on the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb; for the great day of his wrath is come, and who can ſtand? Apec.</hi> 6.15.16.17.</p>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:181270:53"/>
                     <p>Theſe are our ſenſuall, proſperous, and delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liuers, ſee what they come to. They are made to be taken and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and therefore they ſhal periſh through their owne corruption, and ſhall receiue the wages of vnrighteouſneſſe, as they which count it pleaſure, daily to liue deliciouſly, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</p>
                     <p>They iudge Chriſt, and condemne themſelues; according to that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine; Qui pro modica delectatione, dat illud pro quo Chriſtus, ſe tradidit; ſtultum Chriſtum, reputat
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:181270:53"/>mercatorem.</hi> They repute Chriſt no better then a vaine merchant, whileſt for bubling delights they giue their ſoules into the iawes of death, for which he gaue himſelfe, that he might redeeme them from death.</p>
                     <p>But now let the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the Lord look vp, though in the extreami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Egyptian</hi> ſeruitude, though in the fire of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, though vnder the rage of enuy, and ſpeak cheerefully to their ſoules? Why are ye caſt downe? Why are ye diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted? Truſt in God.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:181270:54"/>For they haue a two-fold cauſe of reioycing in the Spirit. <hi>Gaudendum eſt de ijs quae expectamus, &amp; gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum de ijs quae ſuſtine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Preſent ſufferings, and hoped glory, are both matter to feed their ioy. It was the hope of a better reſurrection, that ſo notably confirmed the faith of our Ancients, and made them ioyfull in all ſorts of trials, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing deliuerance. If it were not for this, we are (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) of all men the moſt miſerable. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19. but now (as he ſhould ſo conclude
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:181270:54"/>the moſt happy.</p>
                     <p>Touching the other, <hi>There is no chaſtning, for the time ſeemeth to be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but grieuous;</hi> yet whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee inflicted for ſiune, if ye endure it, God offereth himſelfe vnto you, as vnto Sonnes, and in the end it bringeth the quiet fruit of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to them that are thereby exerciſed. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. Thus much we ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the confeſſion of that holy King, <hi>Before I was afflicted I went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray: but now I keepe thy word. It is good for me that I have beene afflicted, that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:181270:55"/>I may learne thy Statutes.</hi> Pſal. 119.67.71. Or whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they bee afflictions, laid vpon vs by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Church for Chriſts ſake, they tend moſt directly, and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, to the eternall tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, and ſaluation of our ſoules: for this cauſe that miraculouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted ſeruant of God, after hee knew the holy ghoſt had witneſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, that bands, and afflictions did abide him in euery Cittie, for the name of Chriſt, ſet light euen by life it ſelfe, which hee no longer
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:181270:55"/>counted deere vnto him, ſo that he might fulfil his courſe with ioy, and his Miniſtration, to teſtifie the Goſpell of the grace of God. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.24. He accepted them as a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt raiſed to further him towards his wiſhed Citty. For there is no reigning with Chriſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there be firſt a ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for Chriſt: <hi>For here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ye are called, for Chriſt alſo ſuffered for vs, leauing vs an example, that wee ſhould follow his ſteppes.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. By patience and Faith, in tribulations and perſecutions, we are
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:181270:56"/>counted worthy of the Kingdome of God, for which we ſuffer. 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                     <p>Then let vs be manfull in our Chriſtian profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo ſuffer; not ſuffering any longer, that ignominious imputation on vs, wherewith we are iuſtly blotted. <hi>Solus homo non compatitur, pro quo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, Chriſtus patitur.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If we be his members effectually ingraffed, wee will doe any thing wee may, for the glorie of our head, as hee hath done, and doth ſtill for vs; in ſo much that the Spouſe
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:181270:56"/>daily taſting the match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe comfort of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull preſence, is ſo more and more inflamed with delight, that ſhe is euen ſicke of loue. Whoſe cure he vndertakes, and performes by holding his left hand vnder her head, and with his right hand embracing her, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.6. Where can ſhe haue a more wiſhed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory, then in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of her beloued? or what ioy may be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with hers? She finds it is incomparable: <hi>For he is the chiefeſt of tenne thouſand, Cant.</hi> 5.10. His
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:181270:57"/>arme ſupporting her, is the ſtrength of her life, the exile of feare, her warrant of proſperitie; the other encompaſſing her, a bed of reſt, a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of full content, the port of ſafetie, an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable fortreſſe of perpetuall protection: ſo that ſhe ſhal neuer pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, neither ſhall any man take her out of his hands. <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.28. Fight principalities and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, with the mad threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Sodomites</hi> of this world, againſt the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Lots</hi> of Gods heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:181270:57"/>vntill the paſſage of their fiery darts offend them, and their violent prouocations, diſcruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, and perplex them, it is but a cuſtomary combate they haue; and the more vſuall, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is for them: ſeeing all things work together for beſt vnto them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. and their ioy is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo exceeding, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their faith is held in exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, with diuers tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.2.3. they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing permitted either to diſpoſſeſſe, or preuent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, that they may
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:181270:58"/>not decline from a watchfull care, and pious obſeruation of him, through whom they haue victorie, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51. and reſtitution vnto peace and perfect liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Ariſe my loue, my faire one, and come away, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the winter is paſt, the raine is changed and gone away,</hi> Cant. 2.10.11. which his husbandly ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and propitious eye, continued to the happy experience of all that loue him, allures their ſubſcription to thoſe teſtimonies and honourable euidences,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:181270:58"/>which his Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath left of him. That all things are but loſſe, and no better then dunge, in reſpect of the knowledge of Chriſt, &amp; being found in him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.9. That the glory which hee will henceforth reueale vnto them in the kingdome of his Father; farre paſſeth the worthineſſe of al pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſufferings, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. and conſequently, that there is nothing ſo good, nor ſo deſiderable, as to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all. That great Sophy, who diligently imployed his heart (as is
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:181270:59"/>ſaid) in the curious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploration of all things, ſounded a faire and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full palinody from the loue of pleaſure, when he deſcried his owne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berration therein, from the fundamentall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and beginning of true wiſedome, The feare of the Lord. <hi>Prou.</hi> 1. And his father before him, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued it his moſt eminent glory, that he could ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay; <hi>The Lord is my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the inheritance of my cup. Pſal.</hi> 15. <hi>Thou art my houſe of defence, and my Caſtle, thou art my hope from my youth.</hi> Pſal. 71.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:181270:59"/>(Howbeit he might o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe haue largely boaſted of his ſtrength and valour, of humane amplitude, and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) foraſmuch as in Chriſt, nothing auaileth but a new Creature, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15. therein ſtanding a patterne vnto vs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſhould endeuour before all things; <hi>To put on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and take no thought for the fleſh to fulfill the luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi> Rom. 13.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>We haue all things in Chriſt, and Chriſt in vs is all things,</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) therefore vpon
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:181270:60"/>our righteous ſeeking of him, are we aſſured of a conuenient ſupply of all neceſſaries: that <hi>though the Lyons ſtarue, and ſuffer hunger, wee ſhall want no manner of thing that is good.</hi> Pſal. 34. <hi>But ſhall cate the good things of the Land,</hi> Iſa. 1.19. <hi>Wee ſhall poſſeſſe the earth, and haue our delight in the multitude of peace.</hi> Pſal. 37.11. Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> glorifies him by the ſtile of <hi>Theſaurus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deficiens,</hi> an incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, neuer failing trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: So is he more then periſhing food to the hungry, <hi>For my fleſh is
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:181270:60"/>meale indeed,</hi> Ioh. 6.55. not ſuch as our Fathers are in the wilderneſſe and are dead. Drinke alſo to the thirſtie; not like that of <hi>Iacobs</hi> well: but flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the inexhauſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fountaine of himſelfe, which whoſoeuer drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhall neuer bee more athirſt. Iohn 4.14. The ſound and euer healthful reſtauration of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ſicke, and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that caſt their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by repentance vpon him. He tooke our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities with their due chaſtiſement vpon him, and by his ſtripes we are
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:181270:61"/>healed. Iſa. 53.5. Heere ſpake alſo the corporall wounds, of that noble Wraſtler (remembred in Eccleſiaſticall Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) <hi>Blandiua,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Euſeb.</note> as ſo many inſpired mouths, collau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the mercifull power of Chriſt; and the inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible honour of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion, who ſo often as ſhe pronounced, I <hi>am a Chriſtian,</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created, and felt no ſmart of her torments, which were pittifull. Finally, he is ſo all, and ſo eternall, that by the miſſe of him, we are diſabled as withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red branches, from all
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:181270:61"/>ſpirituall fructification, as himſelfe teacheth: <hi>Without me ye can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> Iohn 15.5. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt; to him bee glory, both now and for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <pb n="112" facs="tcp:181270:62"/>
                        <head>HOW GOD WILL accept vs.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>THe poore ſicke child that doth attempt</l>
                           <l>To doe his Fathers will,</l>
                           <l>Ought not of pitty to be ſhent,</l>
                           <l>For ſtriuing to fulfill.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Although he doe not perfect that,</l>
                           <l>was charged him to doe;</l>
                           <l>For reaſon good, requires but what</l>
                           <l>His ſtrength can reach vnto.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>So we poore Weaklings faint and ſicke,</l>
                           <l>Our dutie to diſcharge:</l>
                           <l>If but deſire in vs be ſuicke</l>
                           <l>To ſhew our ſtrength at large.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>God doth accept the fruit we bring,</l>
                           <l>Though ſhort of that we owe:</l>
                           <l>And to aſſure each needfull thing,</l>
                           <l>His bleſſing doth beſtow.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:181270:62"/>
                        <head>A CHRISTIANS ſtate in this life.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>A Man plung'd in the Sea by chance,</l>
                           <l>Doth ſtriue with might and maine,</l>
                           <l>And neuer ceaſeth to aduance,</l>
                           <l>Till he the ſhore attaine.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>But when vpon his neere addreſſe,</l>
                           <l>A new reſurging waue,</l>
                           <l>Of his hard fortune pittileſſe,</l>
                           <l>Giues him ſmall hope to haue,</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>By forcing backe his tyred limbs,</l>
                           <l>About a mile or more:</l>
                           <l>Then louing life, a freſh he ſwims,</l>
                           <l>with feeble armes to ſhore.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>So is this world the Chriſtians Sea,</l>
                           <l>Where he is toucht with ſinne:</l>
                           <pb n="114" facs="tcp:181270:63"/>
                           <l>And doth his beſt, with ſpeed to be</l>
                           <l>Arriued with his King.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>But when he is approach'd ſo neere</l>
                           <l>By grace: he thinkes all well:</l>
                           <l>More ſinfull billowes meete him there,</l>
                           <l>And turne him backe to Hell.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Then new obedience he beginnes,</l>
                           <l>And freely turnes his race:</l>
                           <l>To breake that furious heape of ſinnes,</l>
                           <l>And reach his reſting place.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:181270:63"/>
                     <head>¶ AMBITION the ſecond tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the mind from the <hi>Obiects of true bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>SAthan like a tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous <hi>Nahaſh,</hi> moued by an vtter antipathy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Father of light, and himſelfe the Prince of darkneſſe, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by al meanes to bring the reproach of blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vpon his Image,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:181270:64"/>that he may not be able to lift vp a longing eie to heauen, or haue his heart touched with ſo much as a thought of alienation from his pernicious pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, and curſed gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and foraſmuch, as it was a diſcontentednes with his preſent ſtate, whereby he proudly aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red paſt his reach, to his eternall ruine, and now remaines ſeparated from the Angelicall beatitude, the viſion of God, hee proiects, and attempts the ſame courſe, as cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant (from his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience) hereby to cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuate
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:181270:64"/>the maine Pillars of the world, the wiſe, the rich, the noble, <hi>vt ex An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis daemones faciat,</hi> that he may make them like himſelfe: by holding the pleaſant apples, of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, of honour, and dominion ouer their heads: wherewith nature is ſo rauiſhed, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it perceiueit ſelfe in a Sea of ſorrowes vp to the chin: yet with <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piters</hi> vnfortunate ſonne, it will be catching after them: <hi>Sape quos vita nulla delectat, quos nulla poteſt mouere luxuria nulla aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritia ſubruere facit ambit io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminoſos,</hi>
                        <pb n="119" facs="tcp:181270:65"/>(ſaith <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi>) Oftentimes, they whom no other kinde of life contenteth, whoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſtedfaſtly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the tentation of luxurie and auarice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come criminous and cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable through ambition.</p>
                     <p>Ambition draweth life and ſuſtentation, from thoſe three fountaines, of carnall wiſedome, of wealth, of potency: for (as matter deſireth form) ſo they being incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, and naked endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of themſelues, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy through the miniſtry of ambition for perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:181270:65"/>&amp; cloathing, though it tend more to their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement, and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution, and haply to the extreame dirution of their poſſeſſors.</p>
                     <p>He that hath wiſdome muſt inueſt it into ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, or he becomes deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate; rather then <hi>Herod Agrippa,</hi> being learned, and wiſe would miſſe the honour and eſtimation thereof, hee was conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be ſaluted as a God, and confeſſed to be aboue all mortall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (as <hi>Ioſephus</hi>) which wiſer <hi>Hanno</hi> (as it ſhould ſeeme) ſought more cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:181270:66"/>and painefully, by teaching a bird to ſound, <hi>Hanno eſt Deus,</hi> and then letting him fly, to report it to the world. This made <hi>Achitophel</hi> doe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to himſelfe, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſe, and accounted for his Councell, as an Oracle of God. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.23. he ſaw his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell confounded, and that it was not followed. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.23. And if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doe wiſhedly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh their deſires herein, what is this their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe? true honour? how can that bee? when the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Pauperes
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:181270:66"/>ſunt &amp; ſtulti.</hi> Surely, they are poore, they are foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; for <hi>they know not the way of the Lord, nor the iudgement of their God. Ier.</hi> 5.4. No truly, but a Preface of horror, <hi>The ſtrength of Pharaoh ſhall be your ſhame, and the truſt in the ſhadow of Egipt your confuſion,</hi> Iſa. 30.3. Thus was the wiſedome of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which caried them from God, to ſeeke the ſubſidy of earthly Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces rewarded: and to all thoſe, which by their craftineſſe (for ſo is their wiſedome called) 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. endeuour to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:181270:67"/>themſelues without God, it is menaced, <hi>Your turning of deuices, ſhall it not be eſteemed at the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters clay?</hi> Iſa. 29.16. He that hath wealth, muſt haue preferment, or elſe it wil be thought he hath no wit, which is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt preiudice to the rich that may bee: and when promotion is come, and his heart inſolently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates it ſelfe, in that flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering reuerence, and temporizing obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people, which he hath dearely paid for, how ſtands his caſe with God; <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith hee
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:181270:67"/>vnto him) <hi>thou art vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſpiſed, for the pride of thy heart hath deceiued thee. Obad.</hi> 2.3. And after a while how ſoone it is vnknowne, but his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ſhall be ſudden, (as the Apoſtle ſaith) when the Lord is purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed apparently to exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie his Iuſtice on him, by humbling him from his Throne of celſitude, according to that wofull denunciation againſt the Crowne of pride, <hi>His glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious beautie ſhall be as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding flower,</hi> Iſa. 28. How then, will his repute hold out with Men: or what
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:181270:68"/>profit ſhall he haue by all that went before? That ſtately, arrogant Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Haman,</hi> ſurfeited of this poyſon, and fell into this plague, and from thence, grew contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his inferiours, to his Prince, odious, and laſtly to his euerliuing infamy ſwole to death.</p>
                     <p>The potent man muſt rule, there is no remedy. For this purpoſe did <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom</hi> being a Kings ſon, vſe a ſmooth, affable, and enticing behauiour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Fathers Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, ther by to draw their vnanimous inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:181270:68"/>toward him, for his ſetling in the Kingdome. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. This moued his next Brother <hi>Adonij<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> to exalt himſelfe, and vſurpe where he had no right to rule. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 1.5. But graunt he were, in as ample authority as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy can allow, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in imperiall prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence: what is his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſafer? What more excellent, then was the Gouernors of Ieruſalem, who deuiating through a ſecular and ſenſuall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, from a pious and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall carriage in their functions, were iuſtly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:181270:69"/>by God himſelfe with the aſperſion of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, polluted, and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, and abandoned with a fearefull deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 4.1.</p>
                     <p>The obiect of Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not euer tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: but ſometimes doth it collimate, at things ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall: but in a preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and prohibited man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, whereby our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded ſtriuing to enter in at the ſtreight gate, is hindered by vaine and ignorant petition: as we ſee in <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> the ſonnes of <hi>Zebedeus,</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:181270:69"/>vnto Chriſt, that they might ſit one at his right hand, and the other at his left hand, in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.37. A courſe in familiar practiſe with many, that will beſtow ſome time onely in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king requeſt for the matchleſſe priuiledge of inhabiting the manſions in Gods houſe, as if they were ſtreight-waies wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to enter: not reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting how Gods promiſe (that they which aske ſhall receiue) is limited to thoſe onely that aske in faith, and labour in ſanctitie of life thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to:
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:181270:70"/>and that none others can receiue, neither ſhal, becauſe they aske amiſſe, as the Lord himſelfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, <hi>When ye ſhall ſtretch out your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you, and though ye make many pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers I will not heare: for your hands are full of blood.</hi> Iſa. 1.15. they were not cleanſed from their ſinnes.</p>
                     <p>Sometimes it leuels at diuine and ſacred gifts, paſt our fittingneſſe, and capacity: ſuch was the ambition of <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer, that offered money to buy the power
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:181270:70"/>of giuing the holy ghoſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.19. And of this are they notoriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious, that not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with that courſe, wherein they are confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, by a lawfull vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doe couet, and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly take vpon them the offices, and perſons of more worthy men: as the Plough-man, when he wil ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire, and the mechanicall <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiſt</hi> be a Preacher.</p>
                     <p>To this is allied, that Ambition of hypocrites, (that I may not preſent the Name of pragmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Nouatians) whereby
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:181270:71"/>they intrude into Chriſts ſheepe-fold, as if they were faithfull members of the Saints fociety, and deſeruing an equall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for onely waſhing the outſide of the Cuppe and Platter. Theſe are knowne to God by their hearts, to man by their fruits, they ſweare by the Name of the Lord, and make mention of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but not in truth, nor in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.1. When they are inuited to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, &amp; the Lord (moſt ready to forgiue) promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thereupon that hee
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:181270:71"/>will returne vnto them: the pride of heart hath ſo lifted them vp, that they cannot ſee from whence they ſhould returne; <hi>Wherein</hi> (ſay they) <hi>ſhall we returne? Wherein haue we ſpoyled thee? Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>Per arrogantiam deprauan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quum paratiores ſunt mort, quam corripi, (as wel</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregorie) they are ſo corrupted with arrogance, that they had rather ſuffer death the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rebuke:</hi> ſo much their ſoule delighteth in their abhominations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.3. But <hi>how long,</hi> (cry the godly) <hi>how long Lord holy and true, doeſt thou not
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:181270:72"/>iudge them? Apoc.</hi> 6. This is the firſt part of their iudgement, that though they deceiue for a time, as the Deuil <hi>Iudas,</hi> valed in his Apoſtleſhip: Yet ſhall they bee vncaſed to tha world (though not all) and to the ioy of the righteous, be viſibly cut off from their communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (though not at an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.) <hi>Though thou exalt thy ſelfe as the Eagle, and make thy neſt among the ſtarres, thence will I bring thee down (ſaith the Lord.) Obad.</hi> 4.</p>
                     <p>The extent of Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is generally without
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:181270:72"/>period. <hi>Empedocles</hi> was not heigh enough vpon the top of <hi>Etna,</hi> but from thence would haue clim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the skies to rule the Heauens, and vndertake the gouernment of the Stars. Some are ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent in their proud conceits, that without all regard of the meane, and end, <hi>Quos vltra citraque nequit conſiſtere rectum:</hi> which only ſhould praiſe their actions to bee iuſt and right, they proceede in hope of an vnattingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſumme of glory. In which reſtleſſe and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe taske, diuers are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:181270:73"/>ſundry waies: ſome caring how they may effect vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the wiſh of <hi>Pir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhus,</hi> not onely to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with the ſpoile of one Citie; but after that, to ſubdue and command Countries, till they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Lords of the whole world. Theſe great world deuouring <hi>Helluos,</hi> are epitomized in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of euery Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, where is at the leaſt one ſwarme of Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, that ſnap the Bee; in ſunder, to cram them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with that ſweete, which they haue indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:181270:73"/>gathered: and this not of a few, but euen of very many, till they haue begotten a crew of honeſt beggars, by their impious dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, for their owne dita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and ſo rule rather by force then fauour.</p>
                     <p>Others, like <hi>Perithous,</hi> that made a voyage to Hell to ſteale <hi>Proſerpina</hi> from <hi>Plutoes</hi> bed, ſeeke by rare aduentures of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible expedition, to merit ſame, and popula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, though in ſo doing, they muſt make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of faith, and of a good conſcience, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:181270:74"/>bequeath their ſoules to Sathan. Of this ſort are they, that ſeeke deepe to hide their counſell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord, whoſe works are in darkneſſe, and that ſay, <hi>Who ſeeth vs, and who knoweth vs?</hi> Iſa. 29.15. We may without iniury, take here for inſtance the Romiſh Catholike Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibles, the inſaturable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite of whoſe <hi>Herodian</hi> tyrranny, nothing can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, but a deluge of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents bloud: wherefore they waite with a daily thirſt, &amp; inhiation after that, which Gods tender clemency towards the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:181270:74"/>faithfull profeſſion of his true religion, doth moſt mightily, and admirably diſappoint them of: vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of which their infernal indulgence, they retaine a ſtrong per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion (beſides the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their Maſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; countries ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe) of a Saints remu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration in the heauens.</p>
                     <p>Thus far it appears, that Ambition is, <hi>tinea ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis</hi> (as <hi>Bernard) the fretter out or conſumer of piety, ex remedijs morbos creans, ex medicina longuorem gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, turning the beſt reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies into pernitious diſeaſes</hi>
                        <pb n="138" facs="tcp:181270:75"/>Which is alſo <hi>Cathedra peſtilentiae,</hi> (as Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine) the ſeat of peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> and a cruell plague to the Church of God. For they which loue to haue preheminence, doe enuiouſly oppoſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their mouths againſt Chriſts Paſtors; and ſo ſtop (what lieth in them) the Gold ſanded current of his glorious Goſpell. Thus Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth of <hi>Diotrephes: I wrote vnto the Church, but he which loueth to haue the preheminence among them, receiueth vs not, but pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth againſt vs, with mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:181270:75"/>words, and not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with content, neither hee himſelfe receiueth the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but forbiddeth them that would, and thruſteth them out of the Church.</hi> 3. <hi>Epiſt. Ioh.</hi> 9.10.</p>
                     <p>Furthermore, it is in our Aduerſaries, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Nurſe of ſtrife, raylings, euil ſurmiſings, and vaine diſputations, (which beget in the minds of the vnreſolued, often doubtings, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the truth, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times tranſlating them into the fearefull ſtate of Apoſtaſie, whereof ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are not ſcant this
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:181270:76"/>day.) <hi>If any man</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) teach otherwiſe, and conſenteth not to the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome words of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and to the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine which is according to godlineſſe, hee is puft vp (through ambition) and knoweth nothing, but do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth about queſtions, and ſtrife of words, &amp;c. from ſuch ſeparate thy ſelfe.</hi> 1. Tim. 6.3.</p>
                     <p>But if any <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> ſhould heere enter an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology for Ambition; ſaying, they could not riſe without it: foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as nothing is more proſperouſly atchieued,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:181270:76"/>then what is attempted with importunate deſire and dignitie, is the life of nobilitie; it may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for farther reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſuch an earneſt will, to aſpire to ciuill dignity (before ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and deſert make way vnto it, whereby there may be a likelihood of the anſwerable perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of thoſe weightie duties, which are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in ſo high a calling) is contrary to true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation; which being one of the moſt notable vertues of a reſolute Chriſtian, that other, by
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:181270:77"/>conſequence, is iuſtly branded for a hatefull ſinne: and therefore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy the entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Noble hearts; whither S. <hi>Bernard</hi> as a carefull Watch-man, for the good of the Church, highly commendeth a better gueſt, in this his feeling confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him. <hi>Dignus eſt plane morte, qui tibi Chriſte, recuſat vinere &amp; qui tibi non ſapit, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, &amp; qui curat eſſe, niſi propter te, pro nihilo eſt, &amp; plane nihil eſt.</hi> Chriſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſt bee the obiect of our wiſdome, of our life, of our being; that wee
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:181270:77"/>may liue to bee wiſe in him, and be wiſe to bee found in him, or elſe our ſentence ends not, in <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus morte,</hi> but in <hi>morte morieris,</hi> Thou ſhalt dye the death; for whileſt we delude our ſelues in the glory of a fleſhly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, we incurre not onely the cenſure of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fooles: but that more ſtrict one, <hi>Nihil ſumus,</hi> whatſoeuer wee are, wee are nothing in eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God. To aſpire vnto Chriſt with the wing of ſpirituall graces, and celeſtiall vertues, is the onely true Nobilitie,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:181270:78"/>and the beauty of both the other; of the natural, which is deriued from Parents; and of the ciuill which is impoſed by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nobilitie</hi> (ſaith <hi>Boeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us) eſt laus quaedam proue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens ex merit is parentum.</hi> It is a certaine praiſe, iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing from the merits of the Parents: Thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating, our Anceſtors to haue gone through the Temple of Vertue, to the Temple of Honor, and deſeruedly to haue reached their dignitie: which ſo long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an honourable praiſe
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:181270:78"/>to their poſterity, as they hold on a correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with them in vertue: but if otherwiſe they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit their Nobility, and not the ſoule by which it liues; they doe not onely demoliſh the <hi>Trophe</hi> of their Fathers worthines, but open the paſſage of iuſt diſhonour to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For who ſeeing a letter of Gold in a mud wall, wil not iudge it out of its place, and where grace and vertue haue not their character in the forehead, and poliſh the actions, that face is to foule, that heart to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:181270:79"/>of the faire titles, Chriſtian and Noble.</p>
                     <p>A great Man ſhould be like the Sunne, which as it is more excellent then the other Planets, ſo it ſendeth forth more light, that he may ſay as <hi>Paul: Brethren, be ye follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of me, and looke on them which walke ſo, as yee haue vs for an enſample.</hi> Phil. 3.17.</p>
                     <p>It is memorable of him, that beeing a King, thought nothing could ſuit better with Maieſty, then wiſedome to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne his people: and therefore the Ambition
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:181270:79"/>of all other things ſepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; he asked of God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that, wherewith honor and riches ſtand bound: but are not the principal. The affluence of honour and riches which are to vertue, no better then <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſta nouerca,</hi> checking her ouer preciſeneſſe, for awaking the conſcience to looke ſcornefully vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Ambition and Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, are not to be ſought or coueted of thoſe that ſtand charged with the adminiſtration of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale: but wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome principally to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſe, and cleanſe the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:181270:80"/>heart of thoſe choaking corruptions, that it may be free, for the lodging of equitie, iuſtice, and liberalitie. For they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it were) the Eaſt, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> cals <hi>Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum Coeli,</hi> or (for them more aptly) <hi>dextram Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae,</hi> it is naturall to their high aſcent, and dexterious location for vertue to riſe, but neuer to ſet in them.</p>
                     <p>What could be more preiudiciall to the States of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> then that the Prophet (hauing nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated thoſe duties, which are pertinent chiefely to
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:181270:80"/>their eminent qualitie: and he expected to haue found in them) ſhould through their diſſolute diſtemper, and extreame corruption, be enforced to complaine the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: <hi>But they haue altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther broken the yoake, and burſt their bonds.</hi> Ier. 5. in not ſeeking the truth, nor executing Iudgement: by which two, the man in authoritie is knowne to be Gods lawfull and approued delegate and Miniſter.</p>
                     <p>When <hi>Dauid</hi> heard, that <hi>Saul</hi> was about to come vp to <hi>Keilah,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:181270:81"/>the Cittie for his ſake, he inquired of God: <hi>Will the Lords of Keilah de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer mee into his hands?</hi> He made a queſtion, though it concerned the ruine of their Cittie and liues, whither they would betray his innocency; 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.12. noting the dutie of good Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, that they ſhould be ſo chaſt, conſtant, and faithfull, in defence of integritie of the truth, and of a well deſeruing cauſe, as that no hazzard ſhould impell them to peruert iuſtice. Although <hi>Balack</hi> offer large gifts, to
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:181270:81"/>blind the eyes, and allure them to curſe, where they ſhould bleſſe; yet muſt they anſwer, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> to <hi>Naaman, I will not receiue it,</hi> 2. King. 5.16. and as <hi>Michaiah</hi> to <hi>Nahabs</hi> meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger (who prayed him to ſpeake good vnto the King his Maſter, as the falſe Prophets had done) <hi>Whatſoeuer the Lord ſaith vnto me, that will I ſpeake.</hi> 1. King. 22.14. If thou wilt giue me thy houſe full of Siluer and Gold, I will not paſſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the Lord. <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.18. which is to do iuſtly, to loue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:181270:82"/>and to walke with God. <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.8.</p>
                     <p>The tooth of auarice, (for the moſt part) bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth like a fiery Serpent, to the death of the ſoule, hauing made impreſſion, it ſo inflameth, that no earthly medicine can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile to aſſwage it. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, of all others, ſeeme the ſureſt Lenitiue, which yet worke a contrary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; <hi>Non ſatiando, ſed irritando,</hi> as <hi>Seneca,</hi> kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, where they ſhould quench, and laying on more load where they ſhould <hi>exonerate</hi> &amp; ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: for which our dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:181270:82"/>haue to caſt their eyes on the brazen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of their Nobilitie, which if it bee right by participation of Grace, wil cure it by fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall extirpation.</p>
                     <p>For the Nobles of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> when Grace ſaluted <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> in the Parlour of their hearts, diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the world freely, and with all readineſſe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the word, and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Scriptures dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Act. 17.11. their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion was then altered, which as it ſeduced them formerly to a ſecure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on earthly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:181270:83"/>as the eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all props of honourable eminence; ſo being illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, they were ſoone reſolued; that the true and onely aduantagious glory was, that they had learned Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>But let no man endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger himſelfe ſo farre, as once to cope with this fell Monſter, or let in this heart gnawing Vulture, couetouſneſſe, either of honour, of riches, or of the fauour of men, in hope of abſolution at the length by Grace: for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, vpon our reliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome ſweetneſſe from
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:181270:83"/>it, we haue made it habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall vnto vs, and giuen our wretched ſoules a miſerable reſt therein: the remedy wil in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood, ſeeme moſt irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vnto vs, that ſhall offer to diſrooſt vs from our downy neſt of ſuch a <hi>dulce venenum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The yong Earth-worm that had loſt himſelfe in his golden laborinth, though he had direction giuen him vpon his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, and a thred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twound to guide his ſoule to heauen: yet was his heart ſo faſt lockt vp, in the Arke of his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:181270:84"/>that he could not chooſe, but rather make a ſorrowfull proceeding to deſtruction, then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a ioyful iſſue to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. <hi>Balaams</hi> wiſh was for the peacefull end of the righteous, yet though he knew the way vnto it, (which, was to obey the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord) hee ſtill loued the wages of vnrighteouſneſſe, 2. Pet. 2.15. <hi>Aura ſinum ex pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,</hi> lying open to the reward: with this dregge he was ſeaſoned, and of this hee reteined the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour: no: we cannot co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:181270:84"/>our affections, as we would when wee would, after they haue long ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vnder looſe reines.</p>
                     <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſleights theſe inferiour things, which we ſo much ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value, with the ſtile of <hi>tranſitoria mendacia,</hi> fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue lyes, for making no anſwerable performance to their promiſe. The Prodigalls patrimony might promiſe him the loue of the World, this loue a full ſatisfaction to his vnbridled appetite; but it was not long ere he heard that voyce of the world, and found it true,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:181270:85"/>which Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choes from it. <hi>Ego defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. I will faile thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſt would not for all the Kingdomes of the world, fall downe before Sathan and worſhip him; neither ſuites it with any Chriſtian, that hath his feete loftily pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vpon a Mountaine, vily to proſtrate his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions before <hi>Mammons</hi> dunghill (as Ambition bindes him) though he were ſure to winne the whole World thereby: for it cannot be without the loſſe of his ſoule; for this is the lure which
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:181270:85"/>the Deuill caſteth vp to the Fondlings of this World, bearing this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription (were we wiſe enough to obſerue it) <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go decipiam. I will deceiue thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Abraham</hi> refuſed to take ſo much as a thred of the King of <hi>Sodome,</hi> leſt hee ſhould ſay; I haue made <hi>Abraham</hi> rich: Where is this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous reſolution in the ſeede of <hi>Abraham?</hi> where are thoſe Noble Patriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, that diſdaine to bee enriched with the ſubſtance of ſinne?
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:181270:86"/>Looke vnto the Rocke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence ye are hewen, and return true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in whom there is no guile, &amp; ye ſhall ſit down with your Father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in the kingdome of heauen.</p>
                     <p>But <hi>Eſau</hi> that prophane perſon ſhall riſe in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt vs, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs, for repining at what we haue, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull ſeeking what wee cannot with godlineſſe enioy. With much adoe did <hi>Iacob</hi> compell him, to take his bleſſing; who anſwered at the firſt with a contented mind. <hi>I haue
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:181270:86"/>enough my Brother: keepe that thou haſt to thy ſelfe.</hi> Gen. 33.9. Now ſuch is the emulation, or rather enuy of many murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Eſaus,</hi> that if deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Iacob</hi> carry away, but the better part of the bleſſing, though they haue enough beſides, they are at no reſt, till with <hi>Eliab</hi> they haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered their anger, (as he did toward his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, imputing that to pride and malice of hart, which was done by the prouidence and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the higheſt) ſo they in raiſing obloquies
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:181270:87"/>and diſgracefull fames a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. How it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed <hi>Saul,</hi> that <hi>Dauid</hi> was praiſed for his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and renowned victory aboue him, to what height of enuy did it driue him? and how ſeriouſly did he complot his death? Wee muſt haue euery man, all the Manna in his own <hi>Omer,</hi> all the bleſſings on his owne head, all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment on his own back, and all the praiſe to his owne ſelfe, or elſe a grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of enuy will ſtay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, &amp; make vs ſtomack ſick. No maruaile that S.
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:181270:87"/>
                        <hi>Paul</hi> put <hi>Timothy</hi> in mind to <hi>charge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are rich in this world, that they bee not high minded.</hi> 1. Tim. 6.17. For pride (as <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> noteth) is one of the followers of riches, but experience ſhews vs, that in ſhort time ſhe becoms their miſtreſſe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at her pleaſure that ſhe may bee vpheld, <hi>quo iure, quaque iniuria,</hi> hence (ſaith <hi>Auſtine) tolle ſuperbiam &amp; diuitiae non nocebunt.</hi> Riches in themſelues are harmleſſe, if poſſeſſed without pride: for ſhe among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fiends of her family
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:181270:88"/>tertaines that of all other the fouleſt vſury; and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes it in all offices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her houſe; ſhe hath not a delicate diſh of meate, but Vſury muſt bring it to the Table. She puts on a ſtately Roabe, but Vſury muſt pay for it; the Labourers hyre muſt needs bee diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, how? By Vſury. There is a purchaſe to be ſold, and how ſhall pride compaſſe it? By Vſurie. This is now growne ſo entire with the pride of our time, that it is <hi>tota in tota, all in all, and all in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery part,</hi> and in all, the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:181270:88"/>very ſoule of pride. Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry buyes the Deuill, and all his inheritance, with the price of a bad conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; The Deuill brings Hell his whole patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with him, and ſets them into perpetuall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion: And there is an end of Pride and Vſurie. And therefore as Chriſt ſaide, <hi>Take heede of Cone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe,</hi> ſo doth hee in the ſame words, imply this <hi>caue,</hi> beware of Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. I pray you let vs leaue off this burden ſaid <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> to the Rulers of the people: Reſtore I pray you this day, their
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:181270:89"/>Lands, their Vine-yards, their Oliues, and their houſes, and remit vnto them that part of the Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, of the Corne, and of the Oyle, that ye exact of them. Anſwere this as they did, we will reſtore it, and will not require it of them, and therein is your life, (ye Vſurers) but <hi>though a man haue abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, yet life ſtandeth not in riches, Luke</hi> 12. <hi>but they that will be rich, fall into tentation, and ſnares, and into many fooliſh and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome luſts, which drowne men in perdition and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9.</p>
                     <pb n="167" facs="tcp:181270:89"/>
                     <p>But I doubt it were as good to ſtrike vpon <hi>Goliahs</hi> brazen Helmet, as vpon theſe ſinnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion: for if wee affect Vice, we entertaine it as a Vertue; as it may bee ſeene in them, that will keep their fooles at their elbowes, when their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeter attendants ſhall waite aloofe. Flatterie was no fault in the Court of <hi>Alexander</hi> that loued it; but regarded, and rewarded as a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, whileſt hee more eſteemed the vulgar <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi>
                        <pb n="168" facs="tcp:181270:90"/>for reuerencing him for the ſonne of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> then he did the Nobles of <hi>Macedonia</hi> for their loyal and faithfull dealing; ſo where voluptuouſneſſe, ambition, and auarice, get hands to their paſſe, they are diſputed by ſome as neceſſary, by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as conuenient to be vſed, looſing the note of ſinnes. Why ſo? As in Egypt ſometimes they that were vnlearned in Necromancy, were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted infamous: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beſt and wiſeſt would apply their ſtudy vnto it: So not to bee
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:181270:90"/>skilled in theſe blacke Artes, were enough to bring diſeaſe, diſreſpect, and pouerty vpon vs, (beſids the accumulating of other vnworthy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelies:) Therefore to auoyd the tax of being cruel to our ſelues, which Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> layes vpon them that neglect their fame) meaning the good report which a chriſtian ſhould be carefull to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue:) wee in a miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his ſence, will bee tyrants to our ſoules, that we may be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſinners.</p>
                     <p>This ignorance ſprings
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:181270:91"/>from our <hi>non proficiency</hi> in the Schoole of Chriſt, as Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> example effectually prooues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, who being ripe in that meaſure of diuine knowledge, (which is giuen as diuerſly to the Saints in this life, ſo to all ſufficiently toward their eternall ſtate) would not reioyce, but in the Croſſe of Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the world was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to him, and he vnto the world. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame to bee the duty, and practiſe of all well gouerned chriſtians, to hold faſt with the rock
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:181270:91"/>whereon they are foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and not to ſuffer the externall reſpects of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, reuerence, and time-ſeruing to looſen their anchor from this ſhore, and bewitch them from his obedience, on whom they ought meerely to depend, as being wholy his.</p>
                     <p>We are either old lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and too young pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficients, or but yong lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and no proficients, who hauing in Chriſts <hi>Gymmaſy</hi> but one word to learne, haue not yet lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it as wee ſhould. Chriſt faith, <hi>Diſcite a me,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:181270:92"/>quia corde mit is ſum, et hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milis;</hi> We muſt learne of him, humility: but pride <hi>commune nobilitatis malum</hi> that common miſchiefe of Nobilitie, that too common miſery, <hi>imo pene omnium,</hi> almoſt of al men, doeth ſo often put them all out, as they goe about to pronounce it; yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity lies ſo hard vpon vs (deuiating Pilgrimes) if we will be happy, (and happy are we that we can be taught) that we muſt not thinke our direction hard, &amp; thence be diſcou raged from following it; but labour (and thereby
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:181270:92"/>we ſhall be able) to take the low way, which is the right way, for there is no high way, to that high countrey, and heauenly inheritance. <hi>Quicunque deſiderat primatum caele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem ſequatur humilitatem terreſtrem; non enim qui maior fuit in honore ille ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior: ſed qui iuſtior ille ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior.</hi> (as <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi>) Our humility on earth muſt helpe vs to preferment in heauen: for the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable heere, ſhall not (in that in that reſpect) be the greateſt there; <hi>but the iuſt ſhall ſhine as the brightnes of the firmament:
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:181270:93"/>and they that turne many to righteouſneſſe ſhall ſhine as Starres for euer, and euer. Dan.</hi> 12.3. The leſſon is but ſhort: the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſweet: our obedience vnto it, gracious: the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward glorious: therefore deteſting pride the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of prayer, and bane of all godly motions. <hi>Humilitate omnia facto noſtra condiantur, (as S. Auguſtine aduiſeth) let vs ſeaſon all our wordes and workes with humility.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:93"/>
                  <p>CHOYCE, AND APPLICATIONS, Which may ſerue partly for the vſe of the precedent Treatiſe. Not vnprofitable for direction <hi>as well in Sacred, as in ciuill duties. By Charles Goldwell, Maſter of Artes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>LONDON Prined by <hi>Bernard Alſop</hi> for <hi>Iohn Pyper.</hi> 1621.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:94"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:94"/>
                  <head>TO THE WORTHY and right nobly diſpoſed Sir <hi>Walter Tichborne</hi> Knight: the bleſſing of heauen and <hi>earth be multiplied</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <l>SHall not my <hi>hand</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>preſent my <hi>heart</hi> to him,</l>
                     <l>That gaue my feeble armes,</l>
                     <l>more ſtrength to ſwimme:</l>
                     <l>Then faile my <hi>hand,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>to guide thine artleſſe pen,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>heart</hi> forget,</l>
                     <l>good nature vnto men,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:181270:95"/>
                     <l>If both prefer him not</l>
                     <l>to laſting praiſe,</l>
                     <l>That made me happy,</l>
                     <l>in my dyſmall dayes.</l>
                     <l>This be a Record,</l>
                     <l>of your noble mind,</l>
                     <l>Seated in blood,</l>
                     <l>of a moſt loyall Kind:</l>
                     <l>That Prince, and</l>
                     <l>people cannot wiſh to ſee,</l>
                     <l>Hearts better ſtockt,</l>
                     <l>with true integrity.</l>
                     <l>Nor any blame my</l>
                     <l>gratefull heart, that giues</l>
                     <l>Aduancement to your</l>
                     <l>worth, where merit liues.</l>
                  </div>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:95"/>
                  <div type="part">
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Haue entred ſo great a Bond to your worſhip, that I am hopeleſſe euer to ſay (as the indebted ſeruant to his maſter) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your patience I will pay you all: yet doe I not deſire, that vpon proofe of my willingneſſe, your clemency ſhould pardon all. I would not be ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure; leſt ingratitude cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt me; but that hauing iuſtly to conſider, your free and frequent fauours my beſt endeauours may ſtill bee ſtriuing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure your acquittance: ſo ſhall your Worſhip bee
<pb facs="tcp:181270:96"/>ſure not to looſe what is worth the requiting: I hopefull ſtill to receiue thoſe benefits, which may continue my ſtudy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Sir I could make choyce of no better thing to preſent you with all, then what my heart hath choſen to rule, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent it ſelfe withall, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to perſwade you ſo much hereby, that no greater ſeruice ſhall bee wanting, which may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue a promiſe from this briefe Hierogliphick. The ſhortneſſe, is to bee mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the ſtreightneſſe of my time, not by the
<pb facs="tcp:181270:96"/>defect of my loue: the matter to bee examined by my purpoſe of profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting others ſo well as my ſelfe, not in any thing tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of preſumption: the vnfiled compoſure to bee tollerated, for the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the matter. As they are, I heartily wiſh they may at leaſt content you, if not adde a ſcruple to your happy experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The Lord who hath abundantly bleſſed you with many ſweete hopefull branches, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe enrich your hearts with his graces, that you may bee throughly
<pb facs="tcp:181270:97"/>and perfectly bleſſed in body, and ſoule, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more protect, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect all yours to the glory of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Worſhips euer bounden. <hi>CH. GOLDVVILL.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:97"/>
                  <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull my deare Father, <hi>Iohn Goldwell</hi> Eſquire, the continuation of bleſſings temporall: the increaſe of graces Spirituall: and the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of life eternall: be granted and ſealed, by God, and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AMong many your ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and wholſome rules, laid downe, by way of Fatherly aduertiſement, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, this hath beene one, as not the leaſt repeated, not the leaſt worthy:</hi> Efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt vitae quam linguae teſtimonium. <hi>It is better (ſpecially for a Diuine) to
<pb facs="tcp:181270:98"/>make his life, then his tongue, his witneſſe vnto the people: that in being an example vnto his flocke bee may ſaue himſelfe, and them that heare him: wherein howſoeuer I haue failed, or may hereafter; yet I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hereby to expreſſe my deſire (euen by this my reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution) vnto a conſtant ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledneſſe, and compoſition of life. Who ſhall thankefully entertaine the friendly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of any, noting my going aſtray from that which I haue choſen. Sir, that I haue not made the dedication of theſe my labours vnto you, the world
<pb facs="tcp:181270:98"/>knoweth, that vnder the name of Father, you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend (by vndeniable right) both this, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intereſt in mee: and therefore I truſt you will not deny them as an aliene, when they are offered; but accept them as the firſt birth of my hard trauelling youth; afoord them ſuch fauourable entertainement, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, as without too much partialitie you may. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will you, in your affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vnto vertue (I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume) but take it well, that I haue thus diſpoſed part of your right. In which affiance (with the tender
<pb facs="tcp:181270:99"/>of my moſt humble duety) I commit you to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Sonne, Ch. Goldwell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <pb n="1" facs="tcp:181270:99"/>
                     <head>1</head>
                     <p>GOds bounty in beſtowing his giftes, ſhall teach me moderation in vſing them: leſt wronging the purpoſe of his liberalitie, whilſt I exceed, he thruſt me out of the Garden, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field, and giue mee thiſtles in ſtead of figs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>2</head>
                     <p>God beeing wholly, and perfectly good, could make nothing euil. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I bebold my ſelfe, an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, and ſpotted leper, I know therein I am none of Gods making, but of the deuils vndoing; ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:181270:100"/>that I will pray before all things to bee renewed, that hee may acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge me to be the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of his handes, and I haue aſſurance of protection from him, that will take notice hee made me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="part">
                     <head>3</head>
                     <p>The definition of God (ſaith <hi>Casſiodore</hi>) is that hath no end in Sacred praiſes: though it bee an endleſſe worke, duely to praiſe him, I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre to begin: it argues not an impoſſibility of my performance: but the infiniteneſſe of his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:181270:100"/>The heauens are accounted more noble, that execute their office toward their Creator, in a reſtles motion: then the ſluggiſh earth that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to all, by the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and operation of the heauens. It were more grauefor any being earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to imitate the heauens: then waiting for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, to be tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with eartly affections.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="part">
                     <head>4</head>
                     <p>I had rather bee a reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, then a dying Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix: not to haue my ſoule waſted, and deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in the ſweet burning
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:181270:101"/>ſpices of ſenſuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, but from their aſhes, their viler reliques, which may breed my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſt of them, and teach me to loath them, to bee reuiued vnto a ſecond birth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="part">
                     <head>5</head>
                     <p>Of all terrene things, man is maſter: God is Lord: man ſecondarily to commaund, and vſe, God principally, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and finally to take account. I were better with a little well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: then a ſlouthfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant with a large talent: for God that letteth all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:181270:101"/>vnto man, and letteth him haue all, expecteth for the leaſt portion a rent of glory: ſo that my homage, and duety, to him diſcharged, he will ſecure vnto mee, a quiet and contentable fruition of what I haue: when the ingratefull rich, ſhal ſtand at hazzard, hauing forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all, euen their very ſoules, for lacke of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="part">
                     <head>6</head>
                     <p>The Doue, with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue branch in her mouth, brought better newes to <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke: then the Rauen, that returned
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:181270:102"/>empty. So doeth the grace of Gods Spirit, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part great comfort to the conſciences of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in the promiſe of reſt, and liberty: when the blacke intelligencers, mans three dangerous combitants, informe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but matter of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and confuſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="part">
                     <head>7</head>
                     <p>God in curſing Cain, tooke from him the grace of adoption: but not his other graces. As a bird onely admired for the beauty of ſome few fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, hauing caſt them is of no reckoning with the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:181270:102"/>reſt: So were I, depriued of that grace, which is the beauty and crowne of a Chriſtian, curſed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſable, notwithſtanding all other endowments: for as the Sunne ſendeth light to our earthly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and makes them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, and fit for our daily vſe, which are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, in euery roume vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant, and obſcure: So are externall graces, by this of adoption, illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and adorned, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to eſtimation the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo qualified, who by the miſſe thereof is like a faire man with his eyes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:181270:103"/>out. I had rather haue the ſumme of all riches in one iewell, then many iewels of no price: be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther found ſeruing with <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> then ſacrificing with <hi>Cain.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="part">
                     <head>8</head>
                     <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith; All things are vnpleaſant beſides God, and there is no pleaſure but in him: and <hi>Seneca</hi> repreſents the worlds indignity, by the mutability, and danger of the Sea; which he ſaith is troubled in a moment, and where the ſhip now ſayled hopefull, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently ſwallowed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:181270:103"/>vp. Why then ſhould I affect it? if for riches, I may poſſeſſe them, and yet bee miſerable, poore, and naked: if for honours, and ſuperioritie; I may aſpire vnto them, and ſtill bee infamous: if for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, in the middeſt of them, I ſhall haue but a diſtracted conſcience: if it fare better with mee then thus for a time, I am ſure it cannot bee long. But if I delight in God, it is otherwiſe; in him I enioy all things, hauing nothing: true comfort in apparant croſſes, and the aſſurance of glory, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:181270:104"/>diſgraces. I will qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with the world vnto death, to be at vnity with God; trample embroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſhadowes vnder the foote of ſcorne, that my ſoule may bee wholy vacant, for the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, loue, and deſire, of that certaine ſweet and eternall good.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="part">
                     <head>9</head>
                     <p>When <hi>Abraham</hi> in his iournying came to any place, hee ſought before all things, a place to ſerue God in. To manage all actions and affaires, vnder prayer, and Gods patronage, is the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:181270:104"/>of a chriſtian; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to fortune, or to warrant their ſucceſſe from mans proper ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, and endeauour, is meerely heatheniſh. The benefite of the former, is certaine proſperity: the puniſhment of the latter a doubtfull euent. I had rather in vncertaine at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temps, bee reſolued of a wiſhed ende: then in a plaine caſe, bee vnhappily intercepted.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="part">
                     <head>10</head>
                     <p>It was a Tenent of <hi>Apelles</hi> the Marcionite: that none might fitly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of religion: but that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:181270:105"/>euery one ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, as he beleeueth: a fit maſter for our daies, who warranting our blindnes, and freeiug vs form all induſtry in Sacred im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, who will not learne of <hi>Apelles?</hi> The Eagle to the carrion: dull nature, to the dead tree of fruitleſſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: poyſoned hereſie, and voluntary miſtake: But as I am curious not to take Phyſicke for my health, of him that wiſhes my death; ſo will I not ſticke to the precepts of nature, for ray experience in grace: holding it no
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:181270:105"/>reaſon that is not enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſtrengthened, by the rule and warmth of religion; and that but colde religion, which a man will not maintaine, by the force of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: or when hee thinkes it needleſſe to better and confirme it, by reaſoning. As I am my ſelfe natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: I beleeue that God neither heareth blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, nor ſetteth his eyes vpon any enormious acts of diſobedience, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am pleaſed with the relax reines of licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but as I am recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined to God in religion,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:181270:106"/>and haue mine owne eies opened; I know that his eyes behold in all places the good, and the euill: and ſo am timorous to prouoke him. Therefore I would haue none to continue as hee irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly beleeueth, (&amp; I will not bee guided by him, that would be guyded by a woman) but will ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that I may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to the end.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="part">
                     <head>11</head>
                     <p>The bread, and the ſword, which <hi>Abimelech</hi> gaue <hi>Dauid</hi> in his flight from the face of Saul, were more welcome in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:181270:106"/>that his penury, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillos ſtate, then richer preſents could haue been in the time of his ſafetie, and abundance. I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be fedde with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſupplies in my ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity; then finde many friendes in my ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: by the firſt I know who loue mee: by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who flatter me: and therefore deeme worthy cenſuring, that more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and politique, then loyal, and friendly condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, branding it with the note of impiety, as I find it familiar, and cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: whereby men powre
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:181270:107"/>liquor into repleniſhed veſſels, that the ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie may returne vnto themſelues, with aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: and iudge all bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites loſt, where they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be requited.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="part">
                     <head>12</head>
                     <p>I will chooſe rather, to be a begger with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan vnto Chriſt, for the water of life to quench my thirſt, after flying ſhadowes, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vanities, then to haue the well of worldly proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, and ſinfull plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures lie open vnto mee, which is but the ſtirring vp, of an immoderate ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:181270:107"/>after that which can neuer ſatisfie; And to haue my cogitations, and trauaile eaſed, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the procurement of things preſent: then roule the ſtone of that yong man which thinking to get to heauen by kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, loſt his way, by louing his riches.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="part">
                     <head>13</head>
                     <p>It is a ſure rule, that he which wil learn to ſpeak, ought firſt to learne to hold his peace: for ſilence doeth not onely gather knowledge, from the more wiſe, and iudicious;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:181270:108"/>but it taketh notice of their diſpoſitions with whom we are to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſe, thereby helping vs to free our ſpeech vnto them, of diſtaſt: It alſo allowes a ſpace of premeditation, whereby we may reaſon without errour, or not at all. I will vſe ſpeech ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too ſparingly, then too profuſly; for the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of wordes engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth folly: which pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie conceales from a publique diſcouery: the firſt caſteth a iuſt reproch on the author: the latter may mooue a ſuſpicion of ignorance: but it is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:181270:108"/>without proofe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="part">
                     <head>14</head>
                     <p>The <hi>Smaradges</hi> is moſt of value, that is cleareſt from glaſſy pimples. This ſmoothneſſe is alwayes laudable in the heart; in the tongue but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. As bolſterd ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell, argues a crooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and imperfection in the body: So wordes beeing as it were the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell of the minde, are more to bee ſuſpected of lightneſſe, and vanity, for their great ſwelling ſhew, then when they are vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a modeſt eueneſſe, anp plauſible plaineſſe;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:181270:109"/>But as in a cleere vntrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled fountaine, wee eaſily diſcerne without much prying, what is in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome: ſo in a calme, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and ſetled heart, wee find truth, and truſtineſſe apparantly obiected, ſo that we may credit them, without our too curious diſquiſition: or their too verball profeſſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="part">
                     <head>15</head>
                     <p>Contempteouſly to wrong an inferiour, is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to incurre the danger of an equall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, or the miſſe of a pleaſurable office: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Eagle flieth with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:181270:109"/>the helpe of her great fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered wings, yet the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer feathers keepe her warme. Great men may liue maugre (as wee ſay) the vulgar, yet many helps conducible to their eſtate, and reputation, are miniſtred by them, the vntimely want whereof, (if not wiſely preuented) may inferre their preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, not curable by to late repentance.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="part">
                     <head>16</head>
                     <p>The wiſe man contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the ſott, carrieth his mouth in his heart; As a faithfull ſeruant, in a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage., imparteth onely
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:181270:110"/>what he is aduiſed by his Maſter; So ſhall his tongue vtter onely, what it is miſtruſted by the mature deliberation of the heart. Seeing there is no wiſe man at all times, I will endeauour to bee wiſe as often as I can: when I feele my heart riſing to my mouth I will qualifie that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by enforcing ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to my ſelfe, or elſe withdrawing from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: when I finde my tongue ſubiect to my heart: I will ſerue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and doe my beſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="part">
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:181270:110"/>
                     <head>17</head>
                     <p>A wiſe man in ciuil af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires ſhould reſemble the beſt Turqueſſe: In religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous duties the worſt: that which is moſt perfect, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth of his owne vſual colour by day: but by candlelight greeene: So muſt hee vary with the ſtate of his occaſions; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity befits not trouble, but circumſpection: and iealouſie wrongeth fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie. <hi>Dauid</hi> was ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his friends: but marched valiantly againſt his enemies. The baſeſt is neuer ſeene but of one colour, ſo ought his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:181270:111"/>to bee immutable, alwayes the ſame: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in his pious denoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for true chriſtian zeale, neither admits A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy, mutation, nor wauering.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="part">
                     <head>18</head>
                     <p>To bee of great fame, is as dangerous as to haue an ill report (ſaith Tacitus.) Men of great puiſſance, potencie, and credit, through affection of popularitie, or being ſingular, haue the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneſt inſtigations, to ſtrange &amp; haughty enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, and are moſt flex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible thereunto: neuer
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:181270:111"/>foreſeeing the danger till they bee plunged in it. Such is the ſpurre of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, it neuer ceaſeth to pricke forward to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and eminency, till by an vnſatiable purſuite thereof, they bewray a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire rather of domination then of ruling well: and to become great, rather then worthy of greatnes: which yeeldeth foorth the vnſauory fruites of pride, and arrogance in auſterity, and oppreſſion, not of grauity, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in an equall, and commendable gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, growes generally o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:181270:112"/>Therefore in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch ſhould bee cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telous, and prouident making the meanes of their preferment, rather merit then much for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe; and the ende of it, rather well, then good.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="part">
                     <head>19</head>
                     <p>An hypocrite, and a flatterer, are tryed like an Emraud: which beeing rubbed on a Touchſtone, leaues the colour of cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="part">
                     <head>02</head>
                     <p>The teares of a diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Soule, are the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and beſt ſpoken ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:181270:112"/>for ſinne: they pleaſe Gods eye, they pierce his eare, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel him to mercy: though I cannot alwayes weepe, when I pray, yet when I onely weepe for my fins, I pray effectually.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="part">
                     <head>21</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nimrod</hi> prooued his preſumptuous audacitie, and bootleſſe cunning, in deuiſing a Towre to reſcue the people from being drowned, if haply the waters ſhould ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow, as they had done formerly, and ſo haled downe a greater iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on them, then it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:181270:113"/>was poſſible they ſhould euer ſuſteine thereby. I will build the hope of my ſafety vpon Gods mercy, not on the wiſedome of the greateſt Monarch. If I fall vnder Gods hand, he can, and will aſſuredly raiſe me, vpon my ſorrow and ſubmiſſion. If I leane to man for iſſue, in my troubles I ſhall anger my God, and gaine from thence no other aſſurance but of my certaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="part">
                     <head>22</head>
                     <p>The accuſtomed folly of cholericke reuenge may take an end, from that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:181270:113"/>notable precedent <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> whoſe ſeruants were euer happy, when he was angry: becauſe he would neuer at ſuch times cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them. Anger (ſaith the wiſe King) reſteth in the boſome of fooles: and therefore vndoubted wiſedome, it is to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh that vnruly paſſion. It is the opinion of ſome that not to right them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues being wronged, ſhewes them ſottiſh, and inſenſible of an iniury. Rather had I be ſo repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then of a fiery ſpirit, and quarrellſome. <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſius eſt iniuram tacendo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:181270:114"/>fugere; quam reſparendo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perare:</hi> more glory it is to put off an iniury, by holding ones peace, then get the vpper hand by wrangling, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="part">
                     <head>23</head>
                     <p>Since the Phiſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowes better what is good for the patient, then himſelfe doth, I will not doubt of Gods mercy, though I doe not alwayes receiue what I pray for; for being he knowes my imbecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſuch, as asketh often a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, and what would be hurtful, he is no leſſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull in not hearing at
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:181270:114"/>ſome times, then in giuing at other.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="part">
                     <head>24</head>
                     <p>It is a great inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience in that, which the world cals good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, not to ſee what ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth; whereby it either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth the name of good, or elſe ſuch as vſe it account nothing their good, that is not euill: I will leaue with too little, rather then with too much, leſt I ſeeme to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Satan for an Angel of light: and the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals wandering, the path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to heauen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="part">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:181270:115"/>
                     <head>25</head>
                     <p>Warre is not vniuſtly preferred to a miſerable peace,: Then ſeeing car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall tranquillitie, is a very ſpirituall miſery; I will change it, at all times for a godly aduerſity: for the goodneſſe of a thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on the ende: though I taſte the roote bitter, I ſhall receiue a full compenſation in the ſweetneſſe of the fruite, which is heere but green: and ripeneſſe in heauen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="part">
                     <head>26</head>
                     <p>It is bad talking with a madman, not ſo much for that his heart is depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:181270:115"/>but becauſe his braine is diſtempered, and his reaſon for the time peruerted. It is worſe arguing with a foole for though he hath a reaſonable memory, he is madde in the heart: he denyeth God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wil beleeue no truth: he may be held vp as one in a ſwoune by force: but cannot ſtand of himſelfe. I will not ſpende my ſtrength in lifting at a logge, hauing a more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary building to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, leſt getting a bruiſe by the former, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede with leſſe profite
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:181270:116"/>in the latter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="part">
                     <head>27</head>
                     <p>Hee that would bee what he deſires, muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be what he ſhould: the wiſeſt to diſemble, hath the beſt meanes to liue, according to this world: but he that beares true loue in an innocent heart, is onely wiſe to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life: by how much ſweeter the ioy of Angels will be at my conuerſion, then the ſhreiking of hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh furies at my confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: by how much it is better to haue the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Gods Spirit, then of man, and to bee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:181270:116"/>found in Chriſt, then han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging at the breaſts of the world, I will eſteeme an honeſt godly life, before deceitfull, pernicious hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="part">
                     <head>28</head>
                     <p>For euery ioy the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hath, I will chooſe to receiue a ſtripe at Gods hands, and yet liue more contentedly then he: for how can thoſe ioyes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent him wherewith hee is neuer filled, but ſtill hungreth, and hunteth after more. Or how can I bee diſcontented, that vnable of my ſelfe, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe the leaſt grace, haue
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:181270:117"/>this meanes allowed to cauſe vnto me, a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, and eternall weight of glory.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="part">
                     <head>29</head>
                     <p>Of the wicked, ſome heare Gods word wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, as <hi>Herod</hi> heard <hi>Iohn Baptiſt:</hi> other trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their hearing, as <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> when hee heard <hi>Paul:</hi> but neither was of grace, the firſt being occaſioned by the fame of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: the ſecond enforced by the efficacy of the Scriptures. Some vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſe to meddle with religion, as <hi>Gallio;</hi> others ſleepe in the Aſſembly,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:181270:117"/>and heare nothing, as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichus;</hi> others heare, and profite nothing, as the rich man by hearing of Chriſt. They differ in ſhew, they are one in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. I were as good to be vnwilling to heare, as heare, and not practiſe: as good haue mine eyes ſhut, as mine eares heauy, and my heart fat; I am each wayes the deuils ſubiect: and by trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at iudgement if not thirſting for mercy, I am made his fellow; there is neuer a good: the head, the hand, and the foot, cry out together, they are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:181270:118"/>all damned.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="part">
                     <head>30</head>
                     <p>By the principles of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philiſophy, the abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of hony is chiefly ingendered in ſuch regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where the heat of Summer is temperate, and continuall, as well by night, as by day: and by experience, that heart moſt commonly nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth ſpirituall motions, and ſweete contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is of a mild, and temperate diſpoſition, not ſubiect to extreame paſſion, or not often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed therewith: for when paſſion ariſeth like
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:181270:118"/>an angry ſtorme, it toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and troubles the mind, that during the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation therof, it cannot admit the ſetling of any calme, or comfortable apprehenſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="part">
                     <head>31</head>
                     <p>Some I haue knowne obſerue their friends, for a time more then God: that hauing reaped a wiſhed harueſt of profite by them, they might after reſolue to a ſtrict, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious courſe of life, whereto a meane eſtate, and a troubled minde, would not before admit them. <hi>Gehazi</hi> was cleane,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:181270:119"/>before ſuch corruption made him loathſome. <hi>Zaccheus</hi> hauing offered away halfe his goods, and diſſolued his league with the world, was knit to Chriſt in loue and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie, that was before a ſtranger: and as I haue read, the Loadſtone, and the Iron will not meete, ſo long as the Diamond lyeth neere. It is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for our hardened hearts to yeeld vnto God or bee drawne by his word, whileſt the loue of riches ſticketh in them: If I cannot reſolue well being poore: I ſhall not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:181270:119"/>perſiſt in a good reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beeing rich. If in a cleere day I cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern colours, leſſe ſhould I, in a miſt; not at all, if I were blinde: I will firſt ſeeke God, and then no farther. If I want, I know it is my good: for whileſt he is my ſhepheard, I ſhall want no manner of thing that is good for me; Rather had I ſuſteine pouerty for my good: then haue abundance to annoy me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="part">
                     <head>32</head>
                     <p>It is not the meere lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of all, which ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome happeneth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:181270:120"/>griefe: but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning of all things, which is a voluntary for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking of what wee haue, euen whileſt we enioy it, for the loue of Chriſt; that fitly prepares vs, to runne the race of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. Many for lacke of this preparatiue, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not runne at all: others runne but faint by the way, and returne with ſhame, and loſſe of victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as <hi>Demas;</hi> Before I run, I will conſider who hath runne before mee what I runne for; and whom I ſhall encounter by the way. Chriſt led the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:181270:120"/>way: I ſhall follow him: therefore I will be reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute. The prize is a crowne of righteouſnes, which he holdeth in his hand ready to ſet vpon my head, when I ſhall haue ouercome: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore remembring what I haue purpoſely contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and that I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied my ſelfe: neither life, nor death, things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come, nor prncipalities, nor powers, ſhall ſet ſuch a fainting period to my race, but that I will holde it out: for this cauſe I will run naked, and ſtript
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:181270:121"/>of all, by preferring Chriſt before all, that hee may aſſiſt mee with his grace, in all; becauſe knowing who, and what my aſſailants are, how full of ſubtilty, and rage, they may not lay hold on me to my hinderance.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="part">
                     <head>33</head>
                     <p>The naturall man in regard of accelerating death, can ſay that griefe is light to him that can beare it: howſoeuer, it is ſhort to him that cannot beare it. But the child of God dying daily, reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth not griefe by the meaſure, and length: He
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:181270:121"/>taketh vp his croſſe ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, carrieth it hopeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and layes it downe gloriouſly; A naturall death turnes the momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary croſſes of ſome into eternall; a Spirituall death vnto ſinne, redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth that eternity to a moment here, and turnes it to a happineſſe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, in the kingdome of Chriſt. I will not lighten my burden, by the memory of a corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death: but make my yoake eaſie, by dying daily without which to die well, can neuer be.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="part">
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:181270:122"/>
                     <head>34</head>
                     <p>The Laborinth of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is more intricate, and vnſearchable, then the myſteries of diuinity. Man hath a whole world of cauſes, effects, and ends: of ſcruples, and ambiguities, in the one to exquire and diſcuſſe, by himſelfe, and the helpe of his owne inuention, and when hee hath ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his capacitie to the higheſt, he muſt leaue more knots, and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, vntouched, then hee hath cleered and vntyed: and what hee imagines perſpicuouſly reſolued,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:181270:122"/>lyes ſtill in the way of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable oppoſition, as partly true, and partly falſe, in all; like the Sunne, with the better halfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed. But in the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſaluation, if any more cauſes be neceſſary to be known then the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, meritorious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall, which are the Father, the Sonne, and Faith: any other ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, then the ſauing of the ſoule: or other end, but the glory of God, we may finde them truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, by the Spirit of trueth. I will paſſe by that immenſe Vniuerſitie
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:181270:123"/>of Gods inſcrutable wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with admiration: and conteine my ſelfe in the ſuruey, and ſearch of mine owne little world, where I finde a tenement of mortall clay, inhabited with an immortall gueſt: the reaſon whereof in their differences I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue to bee: that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy being framed, out of ſo fraile, and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a matter, ſhould wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lofty be beaten down with that inherent appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion. Thou art but duſt, and aſhes; And thy ſoule contrarywiſe, enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the diuine i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:181270:123"/>of her infuſor ſhould loath to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, an inglorious deſcent to the allectations of the fleſh. The end of their coniunction alſo, that the body, as through the ponderouſnes of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant elements, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineth, &amp; ſinketh downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: ſo through the propertie of innate cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption it yeelding to a ſluggiſhneſſe, ſleepe, and death in ſinne, ſhould by the liuely, and quickning faculty of the ſoule, be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuated, and rouzed vp, to aſſociate her in an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly conuerſation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="part">
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:181270:124"/>
                     <head>35</head>
                     <p>I find an euen carriage is beſt, that may impart curteſie to all; too much familiaritie, and ſecrets vnto none. It was a wiſe ſhift of a noble Romane, whoſe Lady importunate to know what was deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, that day, at the Councell Table (when he could not but in ſome ſortſatisfie her inſtant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand) hee anſwered the Prieſts had ſeene a Larke flying in the ayre, with a golden helmet on his head, and holding a ſpeare in his foote: which being heard, ſhee
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:181270:124"/>broke the matter imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, to one of her maids: ſhee againe to an other of her fellowes, and ſo forward, till it was ſpread through the Citie, and paſſed for currant: but then it receiued a checke, and ſo was ſtaied. Some friends are of that ſort, they will curiouſly diue into ones breſt, and by ſerious inquiſition, make themſelues priuy to the ſecrets of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: to ſuch I will commit no more then what my minde is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged withall, at the preſent, meaning to take
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:181270:125"/>it vp againe in another place: others are faſter lockt; but as faulty other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: though Muske bee one of the ſweeteſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes, it is none of the wholeſomeſt: and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie, though delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, is incommodious for the concomitant diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and following con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="part">
                     <head>36</head>
                     <p>So farre as auncient Fathers accord with holy Writ, I will make vſe of them: and thus, I will ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in my heart, <hi>Bernard</hi> in my mouth, and the reſt of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:181270:125"/>mine eies: for ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe befits our faith: a patheticall, and feeling ſpeech is requiſite in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: and religious prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, are neceſſary for the whole life.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="part">
                     <head>37</head>
                     <p>Humane ſociety is like a Ruby that being put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire certain houres, becommeth afterward of the colour of a burning coale: If I addict my ſelfe to the company of the vertuous, I ſhall bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably affected, if of the laciuious, and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, of a like blemiſhed reputation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="part">
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:181270:126"/>
                     <head>38</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Alfonſus</hi> King of Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, after an oratour had concluded an ample <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagerick</hi> of his praiſes, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered if thou haſt ſaid trueth, I thanke God for it: if otherwiſe God grant mee grace, that I may doe it. <hi>Vicious phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laty,</hi> is now generall Vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, inſomuch as he that praiſeth moſt, pleaſeth beſt: and it is hard to ſay whither that good King did more heartily attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute glory vnto God: or moſt now arrogate merit to themſelues. The faithfull heere, ſee God
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:181270:126"/>darkely through a glaſſe; which may bee a reaſon the greater part ſee him not at all, and therefore glory, in a ſacralegious vſurpation of his due praiſes, as not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging any ſupernaturall efficient cauſe, beſides their owne nature, and dexteritie. If any thing praiſe worthy proceed from mee; I am but the inſtrument, God is the principall agent: It is the effect of his grace, and the manifeſtation of his goodneſſe. God in euery creature, ſet a chracter of his glory, in man his
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:181270:127"/>whole image, that he might bee knowne to bee wholy his, and not his owne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="part">
                     <head>39</head>
                     <p>Cruell inuentions, when flowing from ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious policy, are vſually layd fruſtrate, to the vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the complotters; the proceedings of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> and <hi>Haman</hi> againſt the Iewes, doe witneſſe it; wherein we ſee cares, and anxieties (by due iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice) aggrauated vpon them both, and Gods people ſafely deliuered from the malice of them both. If I be not conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:181270:127"/>I will not feare the disfauour of the mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: their moſt enuious proiects of iniuſtice ſhall bee reflected from the glaſſe of mine innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, to their owne trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and diſgrace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="part">
                     <head>40</head>
                     <p>When the Sonnes of God ioyned themſelues, to the faire daughters of men, they brought foorth no other fruit but Gigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, and monſterous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprings: and when the ſoule condeſcendeth to the ſmooth enticement; of the fleſh; thereon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the conception of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:181270:128"/>helliſh thoughts, which breake foorth into hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and miſchieuous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignements.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="part">
                     <head>41</head>
                     <p>The <hi>Scythian</hi> will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the <hi>Romane</hi> ayre as infectious, and breeding feuers, which is neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, very wholſome: The <hi>Blackmoore</hi> wil deride the <hi>Indian,</hi> as ill coloured, leſſe beautifufull then himſelfe: So cuſtome, and nature acquainting euery one beſt, with his owne, confirmes in him alſo a better liking of it, then of others. I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtome my ſelfe, ſo neere
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:181270:128"/>as I can, to that which is good, that I may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe nothing in others, but what is euill: and like nothing in my ſelfe, but what I cannot liue well without.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="part">
                     <head>42</head>
                     <p>I will not bee to libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in praiſing any, nor to forward; this ſauours of folly; that of flattery: bee his vertues reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, they will ſhine to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as well as to me: if more concealed, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, they ſhall be miſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of the ignorant for al me: and I haply for them, if more particular, in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:181270:129"/>application to my ſelfe, then to others: they will be neglected as leſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, and impertinent; much forwardneſſe, is a a note of indiſcretion, euincing my affectation rather of the party, then of his good parts. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I know of the well deſeruing (though I may ſpeake it publikely for the incouragement of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) yet will I bee no common actor, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſtudious imitator thereof. Elſe am I like a prodigall Painter, that pourtrayes euery well fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured face, he ſees in the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:181270:129"/>ſtreete, and giues them, to as many other as hee meetes; I will more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the worthy after death then before, as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring chiefely their vertues, which are ſimply amiable, and man for them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="part">
                     <head>43</head>
                     <p>When I remember <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> in priſon, I conſider the faithfull in oppreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But being fauoured by his keeper, enlarged by the King, and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be Ruler ouer all <hi>Egypt,</hi> I ſee in that a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull calme enſuing eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tempeſt of their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:181270:130"/>I will eſteeme Gods rodde as a mundifying plaiſter, and hope for cure when I finde it applied: yea I will deſire to ſaile in ſuch ſtormes, that I may looke for mercy, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, which elſe is not due to mee beeing a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, and no ſonne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="part">
                     <head>44</head>
                     <p>Deuotion is the fuell: meditation the fire: prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the bellows. Deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is cold till warmed by meditation, and then burnes not, till kindled by prayer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="part">
                     <head>45</head>
                     <p>Drunkeneſſe is the blab
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:181270:130"/>of ſecrets, the author of friuolous diſcourſe, the diſſolution of amity, the aduocate of adultery, and pandore to the ſoule, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding vertue, and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in a crew of all beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly outrages. I will dread it as a peſtilence, and ſhunne it as a Baſilike, for the loathſome, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous infection: ſeeing it coſts that in a ſhort part of the ſhorteſt day, which hath beene with much care, many yeeres preſerued: a good name: and ſo wrongs the weale of the ſoule before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to God, that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:181270:131"/>then it lies inſenſibly bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the ouerwhelmed dunghill of the body.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="part">
                     <head>46</head>
                     <p>I haue read of a brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that ſought to aduance his credit; for that in one night hee had loſt tenne thouſand crowns, at dice. In temporalls, an honeſt, frugall purchaſing moſt auaileth the eſtate, and credit, in Gods Church: the good vſage and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of our ſtipend is moſt commended, as moſt beneficiall to the ſoule; onely in Satans dominion, his vaſſals
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:181270:131"/>gaine grace by impiety, and thrine by ſcattering; for being a kingdome of diſorder, and confuſion, all things are caried there in a contrary courſe: they are beſt with him, that are worſt with God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="part">
                     <head>47</head>
                     <p>The Sables haue their haire thickeſt in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and cleaning faſteſt to the skinne: and are therefore then chiefely hunted. The faithfull in aduerſitie, are richeſt in good workes, and moſt exemplary in their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and therefore are then much hunted by the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:181270:132"/>Deuill, to draw them to diſtruſt, and driue them to diſpaire.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="48" type="part">
                     <head>48</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iacob</hi> in his iourney to <hi>Haran,</hi> would haue bread to eat, and clothes to put on: ſo let God grant me to feede on Chriſt by faith, and be clothed with his righteouſneſſe, and I ſhall freely confeſſe rhe Lord is my God: and faithfully hold out to my iourneys end.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="49" type="part">
                     <head>49</head>
                     <p>Religion is like the holding vp of <hi>Moſes</hi> hand, when <hi>Ioſhua</hi> fought with <hi>Amaleck,</hi> whereby, if
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:181270:132"/>it be forcible caried with zeale, we are ſure to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with God, for the pardon of our ſinnes, and peace of our ſoules: but if feeble, and defectiue, it giues our roaring aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary the vpper hand of vs. Therefore I will not paſſe the time preſent in looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and vanity, wherein I ſhould make prouiſion for the future: but I will be alwayes labouring to augment my ſtocke of chriſtian knowledge, for the ſtrengthening of my religion: thinking I can neuer bee to couetous of ſuch a good, becauſe the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:181270:133"/>happineſſe thereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, I am ſure, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be to much.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="50" type="part">
                     <head>50</head>
                     <p>True zeale (like the fire vpon the Altar) muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes burne &amp; neuer goe out or as the ſtone <hi>Abeſtus</hi> being once hot, it muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wax ſtarke cold: for if the flame bee throughly extinguiſhed, it becomes from a reall to a bare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall: and then were the caſe mine owne, I know I ſhould ſoon fall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace to a reprobate ſence, and ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hope, to deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen to hell.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:133"/>
                  <head>To the generous my worthy Friend, Maſter <hi>T. A. è Soc. Temp. Inter.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If that you muſe, to ſee your Name ſo ſhort,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My Muſe doth render this iuſt reaſon for't.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I grudge the paper ſhould take any part.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of what is written wholy in my heart.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <p>KInde Sir, you may thinke it fit, I ſhould haue dedicated this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe to ſome very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: that hereby, I might haue taught him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb facs="tcp:181270:134"/>my friend, and Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to mine owne hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor: but knowing that a horſe marred in the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, will euer after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſome iadiſh tricke; and that an ill bred na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, can neuer make a good Friend with all the after teaching; I haue on the contrary, committed my Friend vnto my Friend, where it ſhall bee ſure of friendly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement: were it but my ſeruant, I would not ſend it to <hi>Nabal,</hi> for a churliſh repulſe: much leſſe to <hi>Hanun</hi> to bee ſhorne, and torne, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:181270:134"/>ſcorned, and laughed at: if not my ſeruant; how then my Friend? which being right, and ſuch an one as I deſire to haue, I Kindly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to your ſelfe, which ſhall euer tell you, in my abſence, that I loue you; which (I am ſure <hi>Iſocrates</hi> ſaith) is the propertie of a true Friend: and onely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for me, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent with you, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſuch ſupply of your curteſies, by the minute; that I haue not time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to count them: leſſe, to ſtudie to requite
<pb facs="tcp:181270:135"/>them, till I am parted from you. The God of peace be with you: and guide your ſteps to the glory of his ſauing grace.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your louing Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, and faithfull Friend C. G.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:135"/>
                  <head>Lectori cuicunque beneuolo.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Excipe (quod fas eſt) Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonem tolle Nouatum.</l>
                     <l>Integer, &amp; ounctis, Author, amicus erit</l>
                     <l>Neutamen niſanus videar, nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſe vouere.</l>
                     <l>Omnes ſic vellem, me redama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re pios.</l>
                     <byline>Tui cupientiſ. C. G.</byline>
                  </lg>
                  <p>FRiendly Reader, there bee a great many whom I deſire to haue occaſion to know by the name of friends: which neuertheles I would not chooſe to carry in my boſome, nor make them my familiars: I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued
<pb facs="tcp:181270:136"/>thee why. I deſire whatſoeuer thou art, no exceptions may be taken, but if thy conſcience check thee, amend: know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is more laudable to be a <hi>Damon,</hi> then a <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocles,</hi> a firme friend, then a fawning flatterer. I haue taxed none in particular, (which to doe I euer counted enuious, odious) but made it knowne, that there are ſome falſe, ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louing, temporizing, of all ſorts, with whom I will in no ſort, if I can chooſe, be ſorted.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farwell.</salute>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:181270:136"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Friend.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IT is a happineſſe to haue Friends: but a greater happineſſe not to ſtand in need of them: for they ſerue moſt, in theſe dayes, (like a Gowne, ouer a Ierkin) to keepe him warme, that is warme, already: or as bladders vnder the armes of a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſwimmer to offer him helpe, that can ſhift well enough, without them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 I would haue my friend in one reſpect
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:181270:137"/>like a Gloeworme: to ſhine moſt in the darke: but not in an other, to make ſhew of that he hath not to performe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 I would haue him in one reſpect like a fiſh, that will come beſt to the bait, in rainy weather: but not in another; then to be moſt to ſeeke, when I ſhould vſe him. Or in one reſpect like an Eele: to be found moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in a thunder: but not in another: then to ſlipp from me, when I thinke my hold ſureſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 I would haue him in one reſpect like a Toade:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:181270:137"/>to carry a Iewell in his head (wiſedome:) but not in an another: to beare poiſon in his heart.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 I would haue my friend of whither ſex, in one reſpect like the pureſt metall; to waſte nothing in the tryall: but not in an other: to be common to all, as well, as to my ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 I would haue him in one reſpect like a greene Peaſeſtalke; not onely to ſhew faire bloſſomes, but perform anſwerable fruit: but not in another; to be ſo temporary, and wither before winter.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:181270:138"/>
                  <p>I would haue him in one reſpect like the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leach, to cling faſt to me for my cure: but not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, when he hath ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his fill, to fall from mee.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 I would haue him to me as I would bee to him: when occaſion ſhall make me the Orbe, then him to be the Planet, and on the conrrary: that we might follow one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers motion: and helpe finiſh each others courſe, more then our owne.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 I would haue him like the Rainbow, a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of faire weather af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:181270:138"/>a tempeſt: but not like two together; neither doe I deſire him, of ſo many colours.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 I would haue him like <hi>Heſperus:</hi> though it bring newes of night: yet it ſhines, and giues light, with a ſtedfaſt, and incomparable clereneſſe, aboue all other.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 I would not haue him like a Comet that makes a ſtarlike ſhew, but differs from it, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nature, and place.</p>
                  <p n="12">12 I would not haue him like the twilight to carry the face of day, and night.</p>
                  <p n="13">13 Nor like a ſnaile,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:181270:139"/>that being gently hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and apiſhly talked vnto put forth its hornes, and diſcouers it ſelfe: but with the leaſt pricke ſtriks into the ſhell.</p>
                  <p n="14">14 I would not haue him a Meteore imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly mixed.</p>
                  <p n="15">15 I will be to him a bow of ſteele, to ſhoote his arrow, as well as mine owne, without breaking.</p>
                  <p n="16">16 I could endure my ſhee friend, in one reſpect like a Bee, that is buſie for the wealth of her hiue: but not in another: to ſting me, when I vſe her but kindly, and touch her
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:181270:139"/>ſoftly. Or elſe like a toothleſſe Snake, I would bee glad to poſſeſſe her, when all her poiſon is out. Otherwiſe if ſhee will needs proue treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. I can wiſh her a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sloeworme, blind, and deafe, that hauing a ſting, ſhe may neither heare any cauſe why: nor ſee, how to anoy me with it.</p>
                  <l>Equals are beſt in euery kind,</l>
                  <l>To beare two bodies of one mind,</l>
                  <l>All diſproportion, Nature flyes</l>
                  <l>Friendſhip enſtrang'd from nature, lyes.</l>
                  <p>Were I therefore wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to enioy a Friend of mine owne chooſing; I would not haue him
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:181270:140"/>much greater then my ſelfe: for greatneſſe is commonly attended by ambition: and that ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth, how it is vnfit for Eagles to play with flyes; they cannot riſe by ſtoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, but if they wil build their neft in the Sunne, they muſt ſtill be looking vpward, after it: to looke a ſquint, marrs the grace, and comlineſſe of that part, which ſhould be the ſeat of feare, and reſpect. Therefore ſuch an one, will not, vnleſſe in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate beſtow the heartles comfort, of a minutes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar conference; or a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:181270:140"/>pleaſing aſpect; and to be commoner with the Camelion, will quickly ſtarue mee. It may bee good to haue ſuch a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourite: would hee put into my handes a deed of gift, for mine authoritie, I will ſay ſo to. But for me to gather peables, till I haue promiſed pearles come from India, I had as good creepe into the ground, there to take vp a certaine, and durable reſt, as be ouer wrought, and pined, with an empty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of cauſuall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Relation vnto him will ſomewhat auaile the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:181270:141"/>credit. I am content to iuſtifie it: but to haue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to take vp, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie to lay downe, will imparage the honeſty; yet will I reuerence him as my ſuperiour, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme his proferred cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies: but neuer with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermuch confidence, leaſt through ſuch preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, neglecting to prouide otherwiſe for my ſelfe, I become at length vtterly deſtitute.</p>
                  <p>I would not haue one, though mine equall in birth; yet too rich, being my ſelfe but poore: for riches will tranſport him,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:181270:141"/>ſo farre from reaſon, that if he be a young denizon, and hath a rib leſſe then a married man, he becomes proud, luxurious, and prodigal, which are three paraſites, that will flatter his eſtate from himſelfe, his good liking from me, his fidelitie from all. His clothes are fitted for the Stage of great mens Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, where hee procures, the hierogliphick of the Seruingmans larger ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation in a cleane tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: and the vulgar to ſalute his worſhip: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he bathes his liuer with wine, he muſt purge
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:181270:142"/>his reines with women: to all conuentions of good fellowſhip, an affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, if you ſhall meet vs there, ſtands as firme as an inuitation, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty, in ſuch obedience, doeth hee ſubſcribe vnto his pleaſure; and after he is blowne vp with a fiery whiffe, and that <hi>Bacchus,</hi> hath tyed the wings of <hi>Mercury,</hi> to his tongue, then to euery inſinuating humoriſt, doth he breake his heart by corners, which is round to none; and in the diſſoluing of the diſſolute and drunken Seſſion, hee lets looſe his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:181270:142"/>Angels, to returne him the ſuperſcription of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſocius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If an old Stoick whoſe heremitical affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s haue wandered alone, paſt the cape <hi>de bona ſpe:</hi> he ſhall haue more coſins, then kindred, be better befrien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded then Nature euer meant him, and ſome will rather deriue their alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from <hi>Iapheth,</hi> then they will be excluded his entertainement, which is the blood of their hope, that they ſhall haue the wearing of his ſhoes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death: they hang vp their bagges, as ſpiders
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:181270:143"/>their cobwebbs waiting with his fall, what may fal into them. So that I, once mooued from my ſtation, and looking that the bias of his loue ſhould holde (as anciently) toward me, can blaze no other Armes but a dogge, ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching at a flie, with this Motto, (By chance I catch, or miſſe) Therfore I will not caſt vp my lure, to a Buzzard, when I am ſure to catch the beſt Faulcon by the meanes; I will paſſe no eſtate of my loue to him that will giue me no better ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for my pay.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:181270:143"/>
                  <p>If an Adamite, that hath his Eue, and young euils about him he will in things forbidden, obey the voyce of the woman, therefore not hearken to mine that firſt violated Gods; ſo vnleſſe I bee hers, as well as his, I ſhall ſtand with my foote in the Sunne, and my head in the fire: if I be affected of both, and the children vnnaturall, not yeelding to the Parents will, a law to them, nor ſealing with awfull conſent, what they determine, I ſhall haue loue with a vengeance: no kindneſſe without a curſe;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:181270:144"/>and yet in future time, I, or mine ſtand ingaged to them, for the good turnes done by their Anceſtors without them. I muſt thanke the Kite, for my hens well brooding her chickens.</p>
                  <p>I would not haue him of the loweſt condition, my ſelfe being fairely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate: for ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritie, is like a change, that hath one linke of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, another of thread, which being vſed, is of no durance: as there is no compariſon betweene our eſtates, ſo cannot he proſecute any frienely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:181270:144"/>for me, to the credit of my cauſe, the cauſe that I truſt him withall, being his greateſt credit. Neither can his loue, bee in the incorrupted nature of true friendſhip toward me: but as the Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, to the gould, that vpon euery triall, takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſome of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: he will loue mee, for that I haue, ſo that what I ſhould loue in him hee hath not, neither truſtineſſe, nor loyaltie.</p>
                  <p>But I would haue him indifferently eſtated: ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, diſcreet, and faithful: that by the firſt I might
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:181270:145"/>vſe him (vpon occaſion) to couer my fortunes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, like a two leaf'd curtaine with all, keeping his owne vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered: for beeing by by loue vnited, as two flowers vpon one ſtalke, it is naturall, to receiue our nouriſhment from the ſame roote: one ſoule to quicken two bodies, and with that better part, all ſecondary, and inferiour things, to bee made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, for our ſuſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, elſe were he, but as painting to nakedneſſe, that will not hide it, but make it ſeene the more;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:181270:145"/>for notice taken of our loue; but that it is wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt in the moſt vſefull operation, doth marke vs out for Elephants caſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe, cannot raiſe themſelues;</p>
                  <p>Single that he may bee vacant for me aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; his affections free to himſelfe, not diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with diuers obiects; nor ſurpriſed with the miſtaken merits of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: that I might be to him, a wife, a friend, an ally, a ſelfe, and all in one, whoſe ſeuerall fruition, were more troubleſome,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:181270:146"/>vncertaine, commonly interlaced with ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and griefe. So ſhould hee haue moſt of his wealth, in one Iewell, that is lighter of carriage, and my ſelfe, be an happy heire of ſo many loues; yet would I not be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious to his vertues, nor ſelfe-louing, to ſtop vp that cunduit, to mine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe, whoſe ſprings might pleaſure others, and me, at my pleaſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others: nor deſire to confine the Sunne to mine owne Garden: Let him be curteous, friendly, and affable vnto all, ſo I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:181270:146"/>liue vnder his Equeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiall, to bee cheriſhed with his moſt forcible, and liuely influence: or haue him alwayes for my <hi>Zenith.</hi> If I ſeeme parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in my deſire, to haue him ſingle to me, as I cannot bee to him: this ſhall ſuffice, that where two, or more ſtand bound, the Obligation is the ſurer.</p>
                  <p>In counſell, and difcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as a Seamarke to the Marriner, that by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him in both, I may beware all dangerous paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, keepe a loofe from the extreames of Rocks,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:181270:147"/>and quickſands, &amp; guide the ſhip of my body, ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betweene them both: And I will requite him with this conceite that I am neuer ſecure, but when I haue him in view, In fidelity like a Butlers Box, whoſe heart none may open, to take account of my ſecrets, but my ſelfe.</p>
                  <l>True faith is rare on earth with all,</l>
                  <l>Saith wiſe (but faithleſſe) Inuenall.</l>
                  <l>Aboue the Phenix, builds that Swan,</l>
                  <l>That neuer lookes ſo low as Man.</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:181270:147"/>
                  <l>It makes Arabia for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate,</l>
                  <l>Alone to haue a mateleſſe mate.</l>
                  <l>The world beſides, is not ſo bleſt,</l>
                  <l>To make this bird (true faith) a neſt.</l>
                  <p>Among the inferiour Court Relatiues, there is ſcarce one to be found ſo hardy as a Nightingale, that will for his friend, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure his breſt againſt a thorne: or be ſo watchful, to doe him good in his neceſſity: but like the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile <hi>Hiena</hi> they are euer gaping toward the coaſt that is cleereſt, &amp; turning
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:181270:148"/>with the <hi>Helitrope,</hi> onely to the Sun: if they ſtand in need of you, for the furtherance either of their credit, or commoditie, then you ſhall find them actiue in the addition of fractions: piecing vp ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny broken termes of Art, to make one haulting, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible ſentence: and in multiplication of no ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple numbers of promiſes, when the product ſhalbe nothing, but two ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunes, with a <hi>Vacuum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſtitium</hi> () And if they doe profer, an example of their gratitude, their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are ſo contracted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:181270:148"/>with the crampe of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, that they cannot without much ado be rid of it: which is as much correſpondent to the true rule of friendſhip, as a ſtraw to the ſtrength of <hi>Hercules.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is another kind of politicians, whom vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that mother of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary peace hath made vs acquainted withall, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g whom if we will obteine a friend, (but enioy him long we cannot) we muſt deale as for traſh at Fayres, giue money for him; and hee will after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bee to vs, as <hi>Eſops</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:181270:149"/>Snake to the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, when we haue relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; franked him, then he explode, &amp; ſcorne vs.</p>
                  <p>There is a ſort of gentry, among whom if you taſt a friend, you ſhal find him like muſtard, ſauce for moſt kinds of meat, which ſome like, and ſome loath, to much of him, will make your eyes run ouer: euery one that liſt may enioy him in like maner, &amp; meaſure, but one graine of him, is better then a ſpoonfull for reliſh; he is aloes couered with ſugar, &amp; hath nothing ſweet but the ſuperficies: If you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:181270:149"/>him you are ſped of a friend, as <hi>Paris</hi> was of <hi>Hellen,</hi> that was faire e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: but if you weigh him, he becomes altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as light: he wil make you freely two firme pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in <hi>Darij,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence you ſhal expect to gather ſomwhat for your turne: but wil conclude (like the former) in celarent, with a <hi>nihil minus:</hi> to theſe this is alſo coincident with the reſt, that reproofe, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice will be like a fly, in a dogs eare, they will make them the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fly from you, or at leſt, like a thorne in a horſes foot, cauſe them to halt, ſo long as you vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:181270:150"/>
                  <p>If you ſeeke in a paire of hie ſhoes for a friend, you ſhal find one in appera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, of a ſimple, ingenuous &amp; honeſt compoſition: but hee will ſtand you in no more ſtead, then an addle egge, which ſeemeth faire in the ſhell, till it be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: &amp; then it ſmelleth: his head ſhalbe ſo foxfurred, with old fragments of Law, &amp; preuenting ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, that it wil be hard for you vpon triall to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape from him, with any matter of curteſie, or if you doe, he will make you ſmell of it.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181270:150"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
